[
    {
        "category": "What is the UK, its Values and Principles",
        "questions": [
            {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "To look after the area in which you live and the environment;To look after yourself and your family",
              "id": "T1-01",
              "level": 1,
              "question": "What are two responsibilities that you will have as a British citizen or permanent resident of the UK?",
              "options": [
                "To look after the area in which you live and the environment",
                "To look after yourself and your family",
                "To stay in the UK forever",
                "To promote work in your local community"
              ],
              "explaination": "If you wish to be a permanent resident or citizen of the UK, you should:\n-look after yourself and your family\n-look after the area in which you live and the environment\n-respect and obey the law\nrespect the rights of others-including their right to their own opinions and treat others with fairness."
            },
            {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "Look after yourself and your family;Respect the rights of others, including their right to their own opinions",
              "id": "T12-19",
              "level": 1,
              "question": "If you wish to be a permanent resident or citizen of the UK, you should (choose TWO answers):",
              "options": [
                "Marry a British citizen",
                "Buy a house in the UK",
                "Respect the rights of others, including their right to their own opinions",
                "Look after yourself and your family"
              ],
              "explaination": "If you wish to be a permanent resident or citizen of the UK, you should:\n-look after yourself and your family\n-look after the area in which you live and the environment\n-respect and obey the law, respect the rights of others\n-including their right to their own opinions and treat others with fairness."
            },
            {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "Individual liberty",
              "id": "T3-01",
              "level": 1,
              "question": "Which of the following is a fundamental principle of British life?",
              "options": [
                "Communism",
                "Individual liberty",
                "Intolerance",
                "Inequity"
              ],
              "explaination": "The fundamental principles of British life include: Democracy, The rule of law, Individual liberty, Tolerance of those with different faiths and beliefs, Participation in community life."
            },
            {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "The rule of law;Democracy",
              "id": "T5-05",
              "level": 1,
              "question": "Which two of the following are fundamental principles of British life?",
              "options": [
                "The rule of law",
                "Monarchy",
                "Democracy",
                "Join a political party"
              ],
              "explaination": "The fundamental principles of British life include: democracy, the rule of law, individual liberty, tolerance of those with different faiths and beliefs and participation in community life."
            },
            {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "To look after yourself and your family;To respect and obey the law",
              "id": "T6-01",
              "level": 1,
              "question": "As a British citizen what are your responsibilities (choose two answers)?",
              "options": [
                "To look after yourself and your family",
                "To go to church on Sunday",
                "To walk your dog only during the day",
                "To respect and obey the law"
              ],
              "explaination": "If you wish to be a permanent resident or citizen of the UK, you should:\n-look after yourself and your family\n-look after the area in which you live and the environment\n-respect and obey the law, respect the rights of others\n-including their right to their own opinions and treat others with fairness."
            },
            {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "Look after the area in which you live and the environment;Respect and obey the law",
              "id": "T7-01",
              "level": 1,
              "question": "As a British citizen, you should:",
              "options": [
                "Vote in all elections",
                "Take part in religious activities",
                "Look after the area in which you live and the environment",
                "Respect and obey the law"
              ],
              "explaination": "If you wish to be a permanent resident or citizen of the UK, you should:\n-look after yourself and your family\n-look after the area in which you live and the environment\n-respect and obey the law, respect the rights of others\n-including their right to their own opinions and treat others with fairness."
            },
            {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "To look after yourself and your family;To respect the rights of others including their right to their own opinions",
              "id": "T9-05",
              "level": 1,
              "question": "Which two responsibilities will you have as a British citizen?",
              "options": [
                "To volunteer in a community project",
                "To look after yourself and your family",
                "To buy food in local stores",
                "To respect the rights of others including their right to their own opinions"
              ],
              "explaination": "If you wish to be a permanent resident or citizen of the UK, you should:\n-look after yourself and your family\n-look after the area in which you live and the environment\n-respect and obey the law, respect the rights of others\n-including their right to their own opinions and treat others with fairness."
            },
            {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "The Channel Islands",
              "id": "T1-20",
              "level": 2,
              "question": "Which of the following territories is a Crown dependency but is NOT part of the UK?",
              "options": [
                "The Channel Islands",
                "Shetland",
                "Wales",
                "Scotland"
              ],
              "explaination": "There are also several islands which are closely linked with the UK but are not part of it: the Channel Islands and the Isle of Man. These have their own governments and are called ‘Crown dependencies’."
            },
            {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "No",
              "id": "T11-01",
              "level": 2,
              "question": "Is St Helena part of the UK?",
              "options": [
                "Yes",
                "No"
              ],
              "explaination": "British overseas territories, such as St Helena and the Falkland Islands are linked to the UK but are not part of it."
            },
            {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "Isle of Man",
              "id": "T12-01",
              "level": 2,
              "question": "Which of the following is a Crown Dependency but not part of the UK?",
              "options": [
                "St Helena",
                "Isle of Man",
                "Falkland Islands",
                "Northern Ireland"
              ],
              "explaination": "There are also several islands which are closely linked with the UK but are not part of it: the Channel Islands and the Isle of Man. These have their own governments and are called ‘Crown dependencies’."
            },
            {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "Westminster",
              "id": "T17-22",
              "level": 2,
              "question": "Where does the UK government sitting?",
              "options": [
                "Eastminster",
                "Westminster",
                "Cardiff",
                "Edinburgh"
              ],
              "explaination": "The UK is governed by the parliament sitting in Westminster."
            },
            {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "Crown Dependence",
              "id": "T17-25",
              "level": 2,
              "question": "Territories not part of the UK, but are self-governing possessions of the British Crown is called?",
              "options": [
                "British overseas territories",
                "Crown Dependence",
                "Great Britain"
              ],
              "explaination": "There are also several islands which are closely linked with the UK but are not part of it: the Channel Islands and the Isle of Man. These have their own governments and are called ‘Crown dependencies’."
            },
            {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "True",
              "id": "T17-37",
              "level": 2,
              "question": "Great Britain refers only to England, Wales and Scotland.",
              "options": [
                "True",
                "False"
              ],
              "explaination": "The official name of the country is the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland. ‘Great Britain’ refers only to England, Scotland and Wales, not to Northern Ireland."
            },
            {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "True",
              "id": "T2-02",
              "level": 2,
              "question": "St Helena is a British overseas territory and it is not part of the United Kingdom.",
              "options": [
                "True",
                "False"
              ],
              "explaination": "British overseas territories, such as St Helena and the Falkland Islands are linked to the UK but are not part of it."
            },
            {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "False",
              "id": "T4-07",
              "level": 2,
              "question": "Great Britain refers only to England, Northern Ireland and Scotland.",
              "options": [
                "True",
                "False"
              ],
              "explaination": "The official name of the country is the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland. ‘Great Britain’ refers only to England, Scotland and Wales, not to Northern Ireland."
            },
            {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "False",
              "id": "T5-04",
              "level": 2,
              "question": "St Helena and the Falkland Islands are part of Great Britain.",
              "options": [
                "True",
                "False"
              ],
              "explaination": "There are also several British overseas territories in other parts of the world, such as St Helena and the Falkland Islands. They are also linked to the UK but are not part of it."
            },
            {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "England;Wales;Scotland",
              "id": "T6-06",
              "level": 2,
              "question": "Which three territories form Great Britain?",
              "options": [
                "England",
                "Scotland",
                "Wales",
                "Northern Ireland"
              ],
              "explaination": "The official name of the country is the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland. ‘Great Britain’ refers only to England, Scotland and Wales, not to Northern Ireland."
            },
            {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "False",
              "id": "T7-14",
              "level": 2,
              "question": "The Falkland Islands are a British overseas territory and are part of the United Kingdom.",
              "options": [
                "True",
                "False"
              ],
              "explaination": "There are also several British overseas territories in other parts of the world, such as St Helena and the Falkland Islands. They are also linked to the UK but are not a part of it."
            },
            {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "No",
              "id": "T8-10",
              "level": 2,
              "question": "Is Northern Ireland part of Great Britain?",
              "options": [
                "Yes",
                "No"
              ],
              "explaination": "The official name of the country is the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland. ‘Great Britain’ refers only to England, Scotland and Wales, not to Northern Ireland."
            },
            {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "St Helena;The Falkland Islands",
              "id": "T8-17",
              "level": 2,
              "question": "Which two of the following are British overseas territories?",
              "options": [
                "the Isle of Man",
                "St Helena",
                "Channel Islands",
                "The Falkland Islands"
              ],
              "explaination": "There are also several British overseas territories in other parts of the world, such as St Helena and the Falkland Islands. They are also linked to the UK but are not a part of it."
            }
          ]
    },
    {
        "category": "3.1 Early Britain",
        "questions":
        [
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Hadrian",
            "id": "T10-22",
            "level": 3.1,
            "question": "Who built a wall in the north of England to keep out the Picts (ancestors of the Scottish people)?",
            "options": [
              "Emperor Claudius",
              "Boudicca",
              "Hadrian",
              "Julius Caesar"
            ],
            "explaination": "Areas of what is now Scotland were never conquered by the Romans, and the Emperor Hadrian built a wall in the north of England to keep out the Picts (ancestors of the Scottish people). Included in the wall were a number of forts. Parts of Hadrian’s Wall, including the forts of Housesteads and Vindolanda, can still be seen."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "After the Norman conquest",
            "id": "T11-15",
            "level": 3.1,
            "question": "When was the Domesday Book written?",
            "options": [
              "After the last Roman invasion",
              "After the Viking invasion",
              "After the Anglo-Saxon invasion",
              "After the Norman conquest"
            ],
            "explaination": "William sent people all over England to draw up lists of all the towns and villages. The people who lived there, who owned the land and what animals they owned were also listed. This was called the Domesday Book. It still exists today and gives a picture of society in England just after the Norman Conquest."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "The Iron Age",
            "id": "T11-21",
            "level": 3.1,
            "question": "When were the first coins in Britain made?",
            "options": [
              "The Stone Age",
              "The Bronze Age",
              "The Iron Age",
              "The Middle Ages"
            ],
            "explaination": "The people of the Iron Age had a sophisticated culture and economy. They made the first coins to be minted in Britain, some inscribed with the names of Iron Age kings."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "The names of Iron Age kings",
            "id": "T12-05",
            "level": 3.1,
            "question": "What was inscribed in the first coins to be minted in Britain during the Iron Age?",
            "options": [
              "The names of Iron Age Gods",
              "The names of Iron Age kings",
              "The names of Iron Age fighters",
              "The names of Iron Age flowers"
            ],
            "explaination": "The people of the Iron Age had a sophisticated culture and economy. They made the first coins to be minted in Britain, some inscribed with the names of Iron Age kings. This marks the beginnings of British history."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "The Romans",
            "id": "T13-03",
            "level": 3.1,
            "question": "Boudicca, was a tribal leader who fought against which foreign invaders?",
            "options": [
              "The Romans",
              "The Normands",
              "The Vikings",
              "The Anglo-Saxons"
            ],
            "explaination": "One of the tribal leaders who fought against the Romans was Boudicca, the queen of the Iceni in what is now eastern England."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "King Alfred the Great",
            "id": "T13-07",
            "level": 3.1,
            "question": "Who defeated the Vikings?",
            "options": [
              "King Edward I",
              "King Arthur",
              "King Alfred the Great",
              "King Henry V"
            ],
            "explaination": "The Anglo-Saxon kingdoms in England united under King Alfred the Great, who defeated the Vikings."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Stonehenge",
            "id": "T14-13",
            "level": 3.1,
            "question": "Which of the following monuments is located in Wiltshire?",
            "options": [
              "Hadrian’s Wall",
              "Cenotaph",
              "Stonehenge",
              "Nelson’s Column"
            ],
            "explaination": "One of these monuments, Stonehenge, still stands in what is now the English county of Wiltshire. Stonehenge was probably a special gathering place for seasonal ceremonies."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "St Augustine",
            "id": "T14-14",
            "level": 3.1,
            "question": "Who was the first Archbishop of Canterbury?",
            "options": [
              "St Columba",
              "St Augustine",
              "St Patrick",
              "St Andrew"
            ],
            "explaination": "St Augustine led missionaries from Rome, who spread Christianity in the south. St Augustine became the first Archbishop of Canterbury."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "6,000 years ago",
            "id": "T15-05",
            "level": 3.1,
            "question": "When did the first farmers come to Britain?",
            "options": [
              "2,000 years ago",
              "4,000 years ago",
              "6,000 years ago",
              "10,000 years ago"
            ],
            "explaination": "The first farmers arrived in Britain about 6,000 years ago. The ancestors of these first farmers probably came from south-east Europe."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "The Domesday Book",
            "id": "T15-11",
            "level": 3.1,
            "question": "Which of the following tells us about how people lived in England just after the Norman Conquest?",
            "options": [
              "The Carta Magna",
              "The Domesday Book",
              "The Canterbury Tales",
              "The Bible"
            ],
            "explaination": "William sent people all over England to draw up lists of all the towns and villages. The people who lived there, who owned the land and what animals they owned were also listed. This was called the Domesday Book. It still exists today and gives a picture of society in England just after the Norman Conquest."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Vindolanda;Housesteads",
            "id": "T15-15",
            "level": 3.1,
            "question": "Which two of these forts were part of Hadrian’s wall?",
            "options": [
              "Scunthorpe",
              "Vindolanda",
              "Housesteads",
              "Grimsby"
            ],
            "explaination": "Areas of what is now Scotland were never conquered by the Romans, and the Emperor Hadrian built a wall in the north of England to keep out the Picts (ancestors of the Scottish people). Included in the wall were a number of forts. Parts of Hadrian’s Wall, including the forts of Housesteads and Vindolanda, can still be seen."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "The Jutes",
            "id": "T16-04",
            "level": 3.1,
            "question": "Which tribe came to Britain from northern Europe after the Romans left in AD 410?",
            "options": [
              "The Suffragettes",
              "The Frisians",
              "The Jutes",
              "The Picts"
            ],
            "explaination": "The Roman army left Britain in AD 410 to defend other parts of the Roman Empire and never returned. Britain was again invaded by tribes from northern Europe: the Jutes, the Angles and the Saxons."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Battle of Hastings",
            "id": "T17-05",
            "level": 3.1,
            "question": "William I defeated king of Harold in which battle?",
            "options": [
              "Battle of Bosworth Field",
              "Battle of Hastings",
              "Battle of Bannockburn",
              "Battle of the Boyne"
            ],
            "explaination": "In 1066, an invasion led by William, the Duke of Normandy (in what is now northern France), defeated Harold, the Saxon king of England, at the Battle of Hastings. Harold was killed in the battle."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Scotland",
            "id": "T17-12",
            "level": 3.1,
            "question": "Skara Brae on Orkney is the best preserved prehistoric village in northern Europe. Where is it located?",
            "options": [
              "Wales",
              "Scotland",
              "England",
              "Ireland"
            ],
            "explaination": "Skara Brae on Orkney, off the north coast of Scotland, is the best preserved prehistoric village in northern Europe, and has helped archaeologists to understand more about how people lived near the end of the Stone Age."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Saxon",
            "id": "T17-21",
            "level": 3.1,
            "question": "Which tribe came to Britain from northern Europe after the Romans left in AD 410?",
            "options": [
              "Saxon",
              "Vandals",
              "Gepids",
              "King Alfred"
            ],
            "explaination": "The Roman army left Britain in AD 410 to defend other parts of the Roman Empire and never returned. Britain was again invaded by tribes from northern Europe: the Jutes, the Angles and the Saxons."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "France",
            "id": "T17-31",
            "level": 3.1,
            "question": "From which modern country did William the Conqueror come from？",
            "options": [
              "Italy",
              "Spain",
              "France",
              "Germany"
            ],
            "explaination": "In 1066, an invasion led by William, the Duke of Normandy (in what is now northern France), defeated Harold, the Saxon king of England, at the Battle of Hastings. Harold was killed in the battle. William became king of England and is known as William the Conqueror."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "He become the first Archbishop of Canterbury.",
            "id": "T17-41",
            "level": 3.1,
            "question": "During Anglo-Saxon time, St Augustine led Christian missionaries from Rome to Britain, what happen afterwards?",
            "options": [
              "He become the first Archbishop of Canterbury.",
              "He become the patron saint of Ireland.",
              "He founded a monastery on the island of Iona"
            ],
            "explaination": "St Augustine led missionaries from Rome, who spread Christianity in the south. St Augustine became the first Archbishop of Canterbury."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "South-east Europe",
            "id": "T2-07",
            "level": 3.1,
            "question": "Where did the first farmers come from?",
            "options": [
              "South-east Europe",
              "South-west Europe",
              "North-east Europe",
              "North-west Europe"
            ],
            "explaination": "The first farmers arrived in Britain 6,000 years ago. The ancestors of these first farmers probably came from south-east Europe."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Julius Caesa",
            "id": "T2-10",
            "level": 3.1,
            "question": "Who led the first invasion of Britain?",
            "options": [
              "Emperor Hadrian",
              "William, the Duke of Normand",
              "Canute",
              "Julius Caesa"
            ],
            "explaination": "Julius Caesar led a Roman invasion of Britain in 55 BC. This was unsuccessful and for nearly 100 years Britain remained separate from the Roman Empire. In AD 43 the Emperor Claudius led the Roman army in a new invasion."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "King Alfred the Great",
            "id": "T2-11",
            "level": 3.1,
            "question": "Under which king did the Anglo-Saxon kingdoms in England unite to defeat the Vikings?",
            "options": [
              "Robert the Bruce",
              "King Alfred the Great",
              "William of Orange",
              "Henry VIII"
            ],
            "explaination": "The Anglo-Saxon kingdoms in England united under King Alfred the Great, who defeated the Vikings."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "The Norman Conquest",
            "id": "T2-19",
            "level": 3.1,
            "question": "Which was the last successful foreign invasion of England that took place in 1066?",
            "options": [
              "The Viking invasion",
              "The Norman Conquest",
              "The Roman invasion",
              "The Anglo-Saxon Conquest"
            ],
            "explaination": "The Norman Conquest was the last successful foreign invasion of England and led to many changes in government and social structures in England."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Boudicca",
            "id": "T4-08",
            "level": 3.1,
            "question": "Who was the tribal leader who fought against the Romans?",
            "options": [
              "Claudia",
              "Boudicca",
              "King Alfred the Great",
              "William, the Duke of Normandy"
            ],
            "explaination": "One of the tribal leaders who fought against the Romans was Boudicca, the queen of the Iceni in what is now eastern England."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "The Battle of Hastings",
            "id": "T4-17",
            "level": 3.1,
            "question": "What battle is commemorated in the Bayeux Tapestry?",
            "options": [
              "The Battle of Britain",
              "The Battle of Hastings",
              "The Battle of Trafalgar",
              "The Battle of Waterloo"
            ],
            "explaination": "In 1066, an invasion led by William, the Duke of Normandy (in what is now northern France), defeated Harold, the Saxon king of England, at the Battle of Hastings. Harold was killed in the battle. William became king of England and is known as William the Conqueror. The battle is commemorated in a great piece of embroidery, known as the Bayeux Tapestry, which can still be seen in France today."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "The people of the Iron Age",
            "id": "T6-02",
            "level": 3.1,
            "question": "Who made the first coins to be minted in Britain?",
            "options": [
              "The Anglo-saxons",
              "The Romans",
              "The people of the Stone Age",
              "The people of the Iron Age"
            ],
            "explaination": "The people of the Iron Age had a sophisticated culture and economy. They made the first coins to be minted in Britain, some inscribed with the names of Iron Age kings."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "The Bayeux Tapestry;The Domesday Book",
            "id": "T6-21",
            "level": 3.1,
            "question": "Which two of the following records give us information about England during the reign of William I?",
            "options": [
              "The Canterbury Tales",
              "The Bayeux Tapestry",
              "The Magna Carta",
              "The Domesday Book"
            ],
            "explaination": "William sent people all over England to draw up lists of all the towns and villages. The people who lived there, who owned the land and what animals they owned were also listed. This was called the Domesday Book. It still exists today and gives a picture of society in England just after the Norman Conquest.\nIn 1066, an invasion led by William, the Duke of Normandy (in what is now northern France), defeated Harold, the Saxon king of England, at the Battle of Hastings. The battle is commemorated in a great piece of embroidery, known as the Bayeux Tapestry."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Hunter-gatherers",
            "id": "T7-18",
            "level": 3.1,
            "question": "Who were the first people to live in Britain in what we call the Stone Age?",
            "options": [
              "Farmers",
              "Hunter-gatherers",
              "Tribes",
              "Vikings"
            ],
            "explaination": "The first people to live in Britain were hunter-gatherers, in what we call the Stone Age."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "1066",
            "id": "T7-24",
            "level": 3.1,
            "question": "When was the last successful foreign invasion of England?",
            "options": [
              "1066",
              "1200",
              "1215",
              "1415"
            ],
            "explaination": "In 1066, an invasion led by William, the Duke of Normandy (in what is now northern France), defeated Harold, the Saxon king of England, at the Battle of Hastings. The Norman Conquest was the last successful foreign invasion of England and led to many changes in government and social structures in England."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "William the Conqueror",
            "id": "T9-20",
            "level": 3.1,
            "question": "What English King introduced the Domesday Book?",
            "options": [
              "Henry VIII",
              "William the Conqueror",
              "Boudicca",
              "King Alfred the Great"
            ],
            "explaination": "William sent people all over England to draw up lists of all the towns and villages. The people who lived there, who owned the land and what animals they owned were also listed. This was called the Domesday Book."
          }
        ]
    },
    {
        "category": "3.2 The Middle Ages",
        "questions":
        [
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "The House of York;The House of Lancaster",
            "id": "T1-06",
            "level": 3.2,
            "question": "Which two houses fought in the Wars of the Roses?",
            "options": [
              "The House of Chester",
              "The House of Lancaster",
              "The House of Newcastle",
              "The House of York"
            ],
            "explaination": "The Wars of the Roses were fought between the supporters of two families: the House of Lancaster and the House of York."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "The Canterbury Tales",
            "id": "T10-04",
            "level": 3.2,
            "question": "What stories are associated with Geoffrey Chaucer?",
            "options": [
              "The Cambridge Tales",
              "The Canterbury Tales",
              "The Eastbourne Tales",
              "The London Tales"
            ],
            "explaination": "In the years leading up to 1400, Geoffrey Chaucer wrote a series of poems in English about a group of people going to Canterbury on a pilgrimage. The people decided to tell each other stories on the journey, and the poems describe the travellers and some of the stories they told. This collection of poems is called The Canterbury Tales."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Anglo-Saxon;Norman French",
            "id": "T11-09",
            "level": 3.2,
            "question": "Which two languages combined to become one English language?",
            "options": [
              "Anglo-Saxon",
              "Celtic",
              "Norman French",
              "Viking"
            ],
            "explaination": "After the Norman Conquest, the king and his noblemen had spoken Norman French and the peasants had continued to speak Anglo-Saxon. Gradually these two languages combined to become one English language. Some words in modern English – for example, ‘park’ and ‘beauty’ – are based on Norman French words. Others – for example, ‘apple’, ‘cow’ and ‘summer’ – are based on Anglo-Saxon words. In modern English there are often words with very similar meanings, one from French and one from Anglo-Saxon. ‘Demand’ (French) and ‘ask’ (Anglo-Saxon) are examples."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Robert the Bruce",
            "id": "T12-14",
            "level": 3.2,
            "question": "Which Scottish king defeated the English at the Battle of Bannockburn?",
            "options": [
              "King James I",
              "Robert the Bruce",
              "King Charles I",
              "King Alfred the Great"
            ],
            "explaination": "In Scotland, the English kings were less successful. In 1314 the Scottish, led by Robert the Bruce, defeated the English at the Battle of Bannockburn, and Scotland remained unconquered by the English."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "The Canterbury Tales",
            "id": "T13-04",
            "level": 3.2,
            "question": "Which of the following poems is about a group of people going on a pilgrimage?",
            "options": [
              "A Midsummer Night’s dream",
              "The Canterbury Tales",
              "To be or not to be",
              "All the world’s a stage"
            ],
            "explaination": "In the years leading up to 1400, Geoffrey Chaucer wrote a series of poems in English about a group of people going to Canterbury on a pilgrimage. The people decided to tell each other stories on the journey, and the poems describe the travellers and some of the stories they told. This collection of poems is called The Canterbury Tales."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "The first person in England to print books using a printing press",
            "id": "T13-08",
            "level": 3.2,
            "question": "Who was William Caxton?",
            "options": [
              "The first person to sail singlehanded around the world",
              "The inventor of the radar",
              "The inventor of the television",
              "The first person in England to print books using a printing press"
            ],
            "explaination": "The people decided to tell each other stories on the journey, and the poems describe the travellers and some of the stories they told. This collection of poems is called The Canterbury Tales. It was one of the first books to be printed by William Caxton, the first person in England to print books using a printing press."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "After the War of Roses, Henry Tudor married with Elizabeth of York",
            "id": "T17-10",
            "level": 3.2,
            "question": "Which of the following statements is correct?",
            "options": [
              "After the War of the Roses, Henry Tudor assigned his son Richard as King",
              "After the War of Roses, Henry Tudor married with Elizabeth of York"
            ],
            "explaination": "Wars of the Roses ended with the Battle of Bosworth Field in 1485. King Richard III of the House of York was killed in the battle and Henry Tudor, the leader of the House of Lancaster, became King Henry VII. Henry then married King Richard’s niece, Elizabeth of York, and united the two families."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "A form of Plague",
            "id": "T17-17",
            "level": 3.2,
            "question": "What was the 'Black Death'?",
            "options": [
              "No rain",
              "Earthquake",
              "A form of Plague",
              "Flood"
            ],
            "explaination": "In 1348, a disease, probably a form of plague, came to Britain. This was known as the Black Death. One third of the population of England died and a similar proportion in Scotland and Wales."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "from London to Canterbury",
            "id": "T17-26",
            "level": 3.2,
            "question": "The Canterbury Tales telling contest by a group of pilgrims as they travel together from ______ to ______?",
            "options": [
              "from Canterbury to Oxford",
              "from Canterbury to London",
              "from London to Canterbury",
              "from Canterbury to overseas"
            ],
            "explaination": "In the years leading up to 1400, Geoffrey Chaucer wrote a series of poems in English about a group of people going to Canterbury on a pilgrimage. The people decided to tell each other stories on the journey, and the poems describe the travellers and some of the stories they told. This collection of poems is called The Canterbury Tales. "
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "1215",
            "id": "T2-12",
            "level": 3.2,
            "question": "When was the Magna Carta created?",
            "options": [
              "1514",
              "1415",
              "1512",
              "1215"
            ],
            "explaination": "The Magna Carta was created in 1215."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "William Caxton",
            "id": "T2-22",
            "level": 3.2,
            "question": "Who was the first person in England to print books using a printing press?",
            "options": [
              "William Shakespeare",
              "William Caxton",
              "Geoffrey Chaucer",
              "John Barbour"
            ],
            "explaination": "William Caxton was the first person in England to print books using a printing press."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "The Hundred Years War",
            "id": "T3-05",
            "level": 3.2,
            "question": "What is the name of the long war that English kings fought with France in the middle ages?",
            "options": [
              "The First World War",
              "The Hundred Years War",
              "The Crimean War",
              "The Boer War"
            ],
            "explaination": "English kings also fought a long war with France, called the Hundred Years War (even though it actually lasted 116 years)."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "The Middle Ages",
            "id": "T3-19",
            "level": 3.2,
            "question": "When did the Black Death take place?",
            "options": [
              "The Stone Age",
              "The Iron Age",
              "The Middle Ages",
              "During Charles II’s reign"
            ],
            "explaination": "In 1348, a disease, probably a form of plague, came to Britain. This was known as the Black Death."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Poems",
            "id": "T4-14",
            "level": 3.2,
            "question": "What type of literature are the Canterbury Tales?",
            "options": [
              "Novels",
              "Poems",
              "Fairy Tale",
              "Fiction"
            ],
            "explaination": "Geoffrey Chaucer wrote a series of poems in English about a group of people going to Canterbury on a pilgrimage. The people decided to tell each other stories on the journey, and the poems describe the travellers and some of the stories they told. This collection of poems is called The Canterbury Tales."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "The Black Death",
            "id": "T6-18",
            "level": 3.2,
            "question": "In 1348, one third of the population in England, Wales and Scotland died as a result of which disease?",
            "options": [
              "Smallpox",
              "Measles",
              "The Black Death",
              "Leprosy"
            ],
            "explaination": "In 1348, a disease, probably a form of plague, came to Britain. This was known as the Black Death. One third of the population of England died and a similar proportion in Scotland and Wales."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "True",
            "id": "T7-06",
            "level": 3.2,
            "question": "In 1314 the Scottish, led by Robert the Bruce, defeated the English at the battle of Bannockburn, and Scotland remained unconquered by the English",
            "options": [
              "True",
              "False"
            ],
            "explaination": ""
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "It restricted the King's power",
            "id": "T8-14",
            "level": 3.2,
            "question": "What was achieved with the Magna Carta?",
            "options": [
              "It increased the King's power",
              "It restricted the King's power",
              "abolished slavery",
              "Every prisoner has a right to a court hearing"
            ],
            "explaination": "The Magna Carta established the idea that even the king was subject to the law. It protected the rights of the nobility and restricted the king’s power to collect taxes or to make or change laws."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Peasants who had a small area of their lord’s agricultural land",
            "id": "T9-16",
            "level": 3.2,
            "question": "During the Middle Ages, who were the serfs?",
            "options": [
              "Noblemen who formed part of the king’s council of advisers",
              "Peasants who had a small area of their lord’s agricultural land",
              "New social classes who are the owners of large areas of land (later called the gentry)",
              "Soldiers who fought at the Battle of Trafalgar"
            ],
            "explaination": "The king gave land to his lords in return for help in war. Landowners had to send certain numbers of men to serve in the army. Some peasants had their own land but most were serfs."
          }
        ]
    },
    {
        "category": "3.3 The Tudors and Stuarts",
        "questions":
        [
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "1588",
            "id": "T1-12",
            "level": 3.3,
            "question": "When did the English defeat the Spanish Armada?",
            "options": [
              "1066",
              "1254",
              "1466",
              "1588"
            ],
            "explaination": "In 1588 the English defeated the Spanish Armada."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Oliver Cromwell",
            "id": "T1-23",
            "level": 3.3,
            "question": "Who was given the title of Lord Protector?",
            "options": [
              "Charles I",
              "Charles II",
              "Oliver Cromwell",
              "Winston Churchill"
            ],
            "explaination": "Oliver Cromwell was given the title of Lord Protector and ruled until his death in 1658."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Spain",
            "id": "T10-16",
            "level": 3.3,
            "question": "During the reign of Elizabeth I, a large fleet of ships was sent to England to conquer the country and to restore Catholicism, where did this fleet come from?",
            "options": [
              "France",
              "Spain",
              "Italy",
              "Portugal"
            ],
            "explaination": "he more extreme Protestants. In this way, she avoided any serious religious conflict within England. Elizabeth became one of the most popular monarchs in English history, particularly after 1588, when the English defeated the Spanish Armada (a large fleet of ships), which had been sent by Spain to conquer England and restore Catholicism."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "That every prisoner has a right to a court hearing",
            "id": "T10-17",
            "level": 3.3,
            "question": "What did the Habeas Corpus Act introduce?",
            "options": [
              "Measures to improve the conditions of workers",
              "That every prisoner has a right to a court hearing",
              "Financial help for the unemployed, old-age pensions and free school meals",
              "Increased the number of people with the right to vote"
            ],
            "explaination": "The Habeas Corpus Act became law in 1679. This was a very important piece of legislation which remains relevant today. Habeas corpus is Latin for ‘you must present the person in court’. The Act guaranteed that no one could be held prisoner unlawfully. Every prisoner has a right to a court hearing."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "The discovery of gravity",
            "id": "T10-20",
            "level": 3.3,
            "question": "What was Isaac Newton known for?",
            "options": [
              "The discovery of steam power",
              "The discovery of gravity",
              "The discovery of insulin",
              "The discovery of DNA"
            ],
            "explaination": "Isaac Newton first became interested in science when he studied at Cambridge University. He became an important figure in the field. His most famous published work was Philosophiae Naturalis Principia Mathematica(‘Mathematical Principles of Natural Philosophy’), which showed how gravity applied to the whole universe. Newton also discovered that white light is made up of the colours of the rainbow."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Spain",
            "id": "T11-11",
            "level": 3.3,
            "question": "Where did the Spanish Armada come from?",
            "options": [
              "Germany",
              "Italy",
              "France",
              "Spain"
            ],
            "explaination": "Elizabeth became one of the most popular monarchs in English history, particularly after 1588, when the English defeated the Spanish Armada (a large fleet of ships), which had been sent by Spain to conquer England and restore Catholicism."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "A Protestant church",
            "id": "T11-14",
            "level": 3.3,
            "question": "What kind of church did Scotland establish in 1560?",
            "options": [
              "A Catholic church",
              "A Protestant church"
            ],
            "explaination": "Scotland had also been strongly influenced by Protestant ideas. In 1560, the predominantly Protestant Scottish Parliament abolished the authority of the Pope in Scotland and Roman Catholic religious services became illegal. A Protestant Church of Scotland with an elected leadership was established but, unlike in England, this was not a state Church."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Sir Christopher Wren",
            "id": "T11-20",
            "level": 3.3,
            "question": "Who was the architect that rebuilt Saint Paul’s cathedral after the Great Fire in 1666?",
            "options": [
              "Sir Edwin Lutyens",
              "Sir Christopher Wren",
              "Robert Adam",
              "Christopher Cockerell"
            ],
            "explaination": "During Charles II’s reign, in 1665, there was a major outbreak of plague in London. Thousands of people died, especially in poorer areas. The following year, a great fire destroyed much of the city, including many churches and St Paul’s Cathedral. London was rebuilt with a new St Paul’s, which was designed by a famous architect, Sir Christopher Wren. Sir Christopher Wren helped develop a British version of the ornate styles popular in Europe in buildings such as the new St Paul’s Cathedral."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Authorised version",
            "id": "T12-08",
            "level": 3.3,
            "question": "The version of the Bible created by King James I is known as:",
            "options": [
              "Approved version",
              "Reformed version",
              "Authorised version",
              "Restored version"
            ],
            "explaination": "One achievement of King James’ reign was a new translation of the Bible into English. This translation is known as the ‘King James Version’ or the ‘Authorised Version’. It was not the first English Bible but is a version which continues to be used in many Protestant churches today."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "To rule without the Parliament",
            "id": "T12-21",
            "level": 3.3,
            "question": "Charles I believed in the ‘Divine Right of Kings’ so he tried:",
            "options": [
              "To restore Catholicism in Britain",
              "To raise money for the Parliament",
              "To rule with the approval of the Parliament",
              "To rule without the Parliament"
            ],
            "explaination": "James I and his son Charles I were less skilled politically. Both believed in the ‘Divine Right of Kings’: the idea that the king was directly appointed by God to rule. They thought that the king should be able to act without having to seek approval from Parliament. When Charles I inherited the thrones of England, Wales, Ireland and Scotland, he tried to rule in line with this principle. When he could not get Parliament to agree with his religious and foreign policies, he tried to rule without Parliament at all."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Hiding in an oak tree",
            "id": "T13-06",
            "level": 3.3,
            "question": "How did Charles II manage to escape to Europe after his defeat in the Civil War?",
            "options": [
              "Hiding in a farmer's house",
              "Hiding in an oak tree",
              "Riding a horse",
              "Swimming"
            ],
            "explaination": "Charles II escaped from Worcester, famously hiding in an oak tree on one occasion, and eventually fled to Europe."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Protestant",
            "id": "T13-11",
            "level": 3.3,
            "question": "What religion did Elizabeth I follow?",
            "options": [
              "Catholic",
              "Protestant"
            ],
            "explaination": "Queen Elizabeth I was a Protestant. She re-established the Church of England as the official Church in England. Everyone had to attend their local church and there were laws about the type of religious services and the prayers which could be said, but Elizabeth did not ask about people’s real beliefs. She succeeded in finding a balance between the views of Catholics and the more extreme Protestants."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Scotland",
            "id": "T13-19",
            "level": 3.3,
            "question": "James I was King of which country before becoming King of England?",
            "options": [
              "France",
              "Scotland",
              "Ireland",
              "Wales"
            ],
            "explaination": "Elizabeth I never married and so had no children of her own to inherit her throne. When she died in 1603 her heir was her cousin James VI of Scotland. He became King James I of England, Wales and Ireland but Scotland remained a separate country."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Spain",
            "id": "T13-21",
            "level": 3.3,
            "question": "Which country sent a fleet of ships to England in 1588?",
            "options": [
              "Italy",
              "Spain",
              "France",
              "Germany"
            ],
            "explaination": "Elizabeth became one of the most popular monarchs in English history, particularly after 1588, when the English defeated the Spanish Armada (a large fleet of ships), which had been sent by Spain to conquer England and restore Catholicism."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "When Charles I was executed",
            "id": "T15-03",
            "level": 3.3,
            "question": "When was England ruled by a republic and not by a monarch?",
            "options": [
              "When the Carta Magna restricted the king’s power",
              "When Elizabeth I died without any successor",
              "When Charles I was executed",
              "When kind Harold died after the Battle of Hastings"
            ],
            "explaination": "By 1646, it was clear that Parliament had won the war. Charles was held prisoner by the parliamentary army. He was still unwilling to reach any agreement with Parliament and in 1649 he was executed. England declared itself a republic, called the Commonwealth. It no longer had a monarch."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "The Cavaliers and the Roundheads",
            "id": "T15-14",
            "level": 3.3,
            "question": "Who fought in the English Civil war of 1642?",
            "options": [
              "The Anglo-Saxons and the Vikings",
              "The House of York and the House of Lancaster",
              "The House of Fraser and the House of Stuart",
              "The Cavaliers and the Roundheads"
            ],
            "explaination": "Civil war between the king and Parliament could not now be avoided and began in 1642. The country split into those who supported the king (the Cavaliers) and those who supported Parliament (the Roundheads)."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Protestant",
            "id": "T15-16",
            "level": 3.3,
            "question": "What was the religion of the Puritans?",
            "options": [
              "Hindu",
              "Sikh",
              "Catholic",
              "Protestant"
            ],
            "explaination": "Many in Parliament were Puritans, a group of Protestants who advocated strict and simple religious doctrine and worship."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Charles II",
            "id": "T16-07",
            "level": 3.3,
            "question": "Who came from the Netherlands to become the British monarch?",
            "options": [
              "Edward II",
              "George II",
              "Charles II",
              "William II"
            ],
            "explaination": "In May 1660, Parliament invited Charles II to come back from exile in the Netherlands. He was crowned King Charles II of England, Wales, Scotland and Ireland."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "The Reformation",
            "id": "T16-22",
            "level": 3.3,
            "question": "Under which name was the movement of opinion against the authority of the Pope during the times of Henry VIII known?",
            "options": [
              "The Enlightenment",
              "The Reformation",
              "The Devolution",
              "Coalition"
            ],
            "explaination": "At the same time the Reformation was happening across Europe. This was a movement against the authority of the Pope and the ideas and practices of the Roman Catholic Church. The Protestants formed their own churches."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Gravity",
            "id": "T16-23",
            "level": 3.3,
            "question": "What did Isaac Newton discover?",
            "options": [
              "Penicillin",
              "Lightbulb",
              "DNA",
              "Gravity"
            ],
            "explaination": "Isaac Newton first became interested in science when he studied at Cambridge University. His most famous published work was Philosophiae Naturalis Principia Mathematica(‘Mathematical Principles of Natural Philosophy’), which showed how gravity applied to the whole universe."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "James II",
            "id": "T17-02",
            "level": 3.3,
            "question": "Who invaded Ireland with the help of a French army in 1690?",
            "options": [
              "Charles II",
              "James II",
              "William II",
              "Edward II"
            ],
            "explaination": "James II wanted to regain the throne and invaded Ireland with the help of a French army. William defeated James II at the Battle of the Boyne in Ireland in 1690, an event which is still celebrated by some in Northern Ireland today."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Macbeth",
            "id": "T17-30",
            "level": 3.3,
            "question": "What is the title of Shakespeare's best known play?",
            "options": [
              "The Phantom of the Opera",
              "The Mousetrap",
              "Macbeth",
              "Mikado"
            ],
            "explaination": "Shakespeare was born in Stratford-upon-Avon, England. He was a playwright and actor and wrote many poems and plays. His most famous plays include A Midsummer Night’s Dream, Hamlet, Macbeth and Romeo and Juliet."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "William of Orange",
            "id": "T17-33",
            "level": 3.3,
            "question": "Who was asked by Protestants to invade England and replaced James II as King?",
            "options": [
              "William, the Duke of Normand",
              "William of Orange",
              "William III",
              "Charles II"
            ],
            "explaination": "William of Orange was asked by important Protestants in England to invade England and proclaim himself king."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Scotland",
            "id": "T17-35",
            "level": 3.3,
            "question": "Elizabeth I never married and so had no children of her own to inherit her throne. From which country does King James I was King before becoming King of England?",
            "options": [
              "Scotland",
              "Wales",
              "Ireland",
              "Australia"
            ],
            "explaination": "Elizabeth I never married and so had no children of her own to inherit her throne. When she died in 1603 her heir was her cousin James VI of Scotland. He became King James I of England, Wales and Ireland but Scotland remained a separate country."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "A Midsummer Night’s dream",
            "id": "T2-14",
            "level": 3.3,
            "question": "Which of the following plays was written by William Shakespeare?",
            "options": [
              "Sense and Sensibility",
              "Great Expectations",
              "Pride and Prejudice",
              "A Midsummer Night’s dream"
            ],
            "explaination": "He was a playwright and actor and wrote many poems and plays. His most famous plays include A Midsummer Night’s Dream, Hamlet, Macbeth and Romeo and Juliet."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "To divorce his first wife",
            "id": "T3-04",
            "level": 3.3,
            "question": "Why did Henry VIII establish the church of England?",
            "options": [
              "To celebrate his wedding",
              "To establish a unique religion in England",
              "To divorce his first wife",
              "To have control over religious people"
            ],
            "explaination": "To divorce his first wife, Henry needed the approval of the Pope. When the Pope refused, Henry established the Church of England. In this new Church, the king, not the Pope, would have the power to appoint bishops and order how people should worship"
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "A fire",
            "id": "T4-03",
            "level": 3.3,
            "question": "During the reign of Charles II parts of London were destroyed, what was the cause of this destruction?",
            "options": [
              "A flood",
              "A fire",
              "An earthquake",
              "A war"
            ],
            "explaination": "During Charles II’s reign, in 1665, there was a major outbreak of plague in London. Thousands of people died, especially in poorer areas. The following year, a great fire destroyed much of the city, including many churches and St Paul’s Cathedral."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Cavaliers",
            "id": "T4-16",
            "level": 3.3,
            "question": "Who supported King Charles I during the Civil War?",
            "options": [
              "Roundheads",
              "Cavaliers",
              "Suffragettes",
              "Serfs"
            ],
            "explaination": "Civil war between the king and Parliament could not now be avoided and began in 1642. The country split into those who supported the king (the Cavaliers) and those who supported Parliament (the Roundheads)."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Tower of London",
            "id": "T4-18",
            "level": 3.3,
            "question": "Where was Anne Boleyn, the wife of Henry VIII, executed?",
            "options": [
              "Stonehenge",
              "Tower of London",
              "Houses of the Parliament",
              "Whitehall"
            ],
            "explaination": "Anne Boleyn was English. She and Henry had one daughter, Elizabeth. Anne was unpopular in the country and was accused of taking lovers. She was executed at the Tower of London."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Charles II",
            "id": "T5-10",
            "level": 3.3,
            "question": "What king was defeated by Oliver Cromwell during the Civil War and hid in an oak tree before escaping to Europe?",
            "options": [
              "Charles I",
              "Charles II",
              "James II",
              "Henry IV"
            ],
            "explaination": "Charles II escaped from Worcester, famously hiding in an oak tree on one occasion, and eventually fled to Europe."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Henry VIII",
            "id": "T5-11",
            "level": 3.3,
            "question": "Who was the father of Queen Elizabeth I?",
            "options": [
              "Edward I",
              "Henry V",
              "Henry VII",
              "Henry VIII"
            ],
            "explaination": "Henry VIII was succeeded by his son Edward VI, who was strongly Protestant. Edward died at the age of 15 after ruling for just over six years, and his half-sister Mary became queen. Mary also died after a short reign and the next monarch was her half-sister, Elizabeth, the daughter of Henry VIII and Anne Boleyn."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Mary Stuart (‘Mary, Queen of Scots’) was a Catholic",
            "id": "T5-15",
            "level": 3.3,
            "question": "Which of the following statements is TRUE:",
            "options": [
              "Mary Stuart (‘Mary, Queen of Scots’) was a Protestant",
              "Mary Stuart (‘Mary, Queen of Scots’) was a Catholic"
            ],
            "explaination": "Mary Stuart (‘Mary, Queen of Scots’) was a Catholic."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "The 'Glorious Revolution'",
            "id": "T5-18",
            "level": 3.3,
            "question": "William of Orange was asked by Protestants to invade England and proclaim himself king. But, when William reached England, there was no resistance and he took over the throne. This event was later Known as:",
            "options": [
              "The 'Great Depression'",
              "The 'Blitz'",
              "The Restoration",
              "The 'Glorious Revolution'"
            ],
            "explaination": "James II’s elder daughter, Mary, was married to her cousin William of Orange, the Protestant ruler of the Netherlands. In 1688, important Protestants in England asked William to invade England and proclaim himself king. When William reached England, there was no resistance. James fled to France and William took over the throne, becoming William III in England, Wales and Ireland, and William II of Scotland. This event was later called the ‘Glorious Revolution’."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Charles I",
            "id": "T6-08",
            "level": 3.3,
            "question": "Which king was executed in 1649?",
            "options": [
              "James I",
              "James VII",
              "Charles I",
              "Charles II"
            ],
            "explaination": "The king’s army was defeated at the Battles of Marston Moor and Naseby. By 1646, it was clear that Parliament had won the war. Charles was held prisoner by the parliamentary army. He was still unwilling to reach any agreement with Parliament and in 1649 he was executed."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Stratford-upon-Avon",
            "id": "T6-09",
            "level": 3.3,
            "question": "Where was William Shakespeare born?",
            "options": [
              "Stratford-upon-Avon",
              "Manchester",
              "Oldham",
              "Lincolnshire"
            ],
            "explaination": "Shakespeare was born in Stratford-upon-Avon, England."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Elizabeth I",
            "id": "T6-11",
            "level": 3.3,
            "question": "Who was reigning in England when English settlers first began to colonise the eastern coast of America?",
            "options": [
              "Henry VIII",
              "Elizabeth I",
              "Charles II",
              "Queen Victoria"
            ],
            "explaination": "In Elizabeth I’s time, English settlers first began to colonise the eastern coast of America. This colonisation, particularly by people who disagreed with the religious views of the next two kings, greatly increased in the next century."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Henry VIII",
            "id": "T6-17",
            "level": 3.3,
            "question": "Who established the Church of England?",
            "options": [
              "William of Orange",
              "Winston Churchill",
              "Henry VIII",
              "Charles II"
            ],
            "explaination": "To divorce his first wife, Henry needed the approval of the Pope. When the Pope refused, Henry established the Church of England. In this new Church, the king, not the Pope, would have the power to appoint bishops and order how people should worship."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Elizabeth I was a Protestant and she succeeded in finding a balance between the views of the Catholics and the more extreme Protestants.",
            "id": "T6-23",
            "level": 3.3,
            "question": "Which of the following statements is true:",
            "options": [
              "Elizabeth I was a Protestant and she succeeded in finding a balance between the views of the Catholics and the more extreme Protestants.",
              "Elizabeth I was a Catholic and she succeeded in finding a balance between the views of the Catholics and the more extreme Protestants."
            ],
            "explaination": "Queen Elizabeth I was a Protestant. She re-established the Church of England as the official Church in England. Everyone had to attend their local church and there were laws about the type of religious services and the prayers which could be said, but Elizabeth did not ask about people’s real beliefs. She succeeded in finding a balance between the views of Catholics and the more extreme Protestants."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "The MacDonalds of Glencoe",
            "id": "T7-08",
            "level": 3.3,
            "question": "Which Scottish clan was killed for not taking the oath?",
            "options": [
              "Harold Macmillan",
              "John MacLeod",
              "The MacDonalds of Glencoe",
              "Kevin MacDonald"
            ],
            "explaination": "All Scottish clans were required formally to accept William as king by taking an oath. The MacDonalds of Glencoe were late in taking the oath and were all killed."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "The Battle of Marston Moor;The Battle of Naseby",
            "id": "T7-15",
            "level": 3.3,
            "question": "Which two of the following are Civil War Battles?",
            "options": [
              "The Battle of Marston Moor",
              "The Battle of Agincourt",
              "The Battle of Naseby",
              "Battle of Hastings"
            ],
            "explaination": "The king’s army was defeated at the Battles of Marston Moor and Naseby. By 1646, it was clear that Parliament had won the war. Charles was held prisoner by the parliamentary army."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "The Reformation",
            "id": "T7-19",
            "level": 3.3,
            "question": "What is the name of the movement against the authority of the Pope and the ideas of the Catholic Church that took place during the reign of Henry VIII?",
            "options": [
              "The Enlightenment",
              "The Glorious Revolution",
              "The Industrial Revolution",
              "The Reformation"
            ],
            "explaination": "At the same time the Reformation was happening across Europe. This was a movement against the authority of the Pope and the ideas and practices of the Roman Catholic Church."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "was executed",
            "id": "T8-06",
            "level": 3.3,
            "question": "What happened to ‘Mary, Queen of Scots’ after she spent 20 years in prison?",
            "options": [
              "escaped to Denmark",
              "was executed",
              "was sent to France",
              "became Queen of England"
            ],
            "explaination": "Mary was eventually executed, accused of plotting against Elizabeth I."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "The Spanish Armada",
            "id": "T8-18",
            "level": 3.3,
            "question": "Who did the English defeat in 1588?",
            "options": [
              "The Romans",
              "The Saxons",
              "The Normands",
              "The Spanish Armada"
            ],
            "explaination": "In 1588, the English defeated the Spanish Armada (a large fleet of ships), which had been sent by Spain to conquer England and restore Catholicism."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "William Shakespeare",
            "id": "T9-06",
            "level": 3.3,
            "question": "Who was born in Stratford-upon-Avon?",
            "options": [
              "Thomas Hardy",
              "Sake Dean Mahomet",
              "William Shakespeare",
              "Isaac Newton"
            ],
            "explaination": "Shakespeare was born in Stratford-upon-Avon, England."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "The Reformation",
            "id": "T9-19",
            "level": 3.3,
            "question": "What movement challenged the authority of the Pope?",
            "options": [
              "The Swinging Sixties",
              "The Glorious Revolution",
              "The Enlightenment",
              "The Reformation"
            ],
            "explaination": "At the same time the Reformation was happening across Europe. This was a movement against the authority of the Pope and the ideas and practices of the Roman Catholic Church."
          }
        ]
    },
    {
        "category": "3.4 A global power",
        "questions":
        [
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "1928",
            "id": "T1-03",
            "level": 3.4,
            "question": "When were men and women given the right to vote at the age of 21?",
            "options": [
              "1828",
              "1918",
              "1928",
              "1969"
            ],
            "explaination": "In 1928, women were given the right to vote at the age of 21, the same as men."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "False",
            "id": "T1-07",
            "level": 3.4,
            "question": "The Bill of Rights of 1689 confirmed the right to vote for all adult men.",
            "options": [
              "True",
              "False"
            ],
            "explaination": "The Bill of Rights, 1689, confirmed the rights of Parliament and the limits of the king’s power."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "In recognition of the contribution women made to the war effort during the First World War",
            "id": "T10-07",
            "level": 3.4,
            "question": "Why were women given the right to vote?",
            "options": [
              "In recognition of the contribution women made to the war effort during the Civil War",
              "In recognition of the contribution women made to the war effort during the Crimean War",
              "In recognition of the contribution women made to the war effort during the First World War",
              "In recognition of the contribution women made to the war effort during the Second World War"
            ],
            "explaination": "In 1918, women over the age of 30 were given voting rights and the right to stand for Parliament, partly in recognition of the contribution women made to the war effort during the First World War."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Constitutional monarchy",
            "id": "T10-15",
            "level": 3.4,
            "question": "The laws passed after the Glorious Revolution marked the beginning of the ______.",
            "options": [
              "Constitutional monarchy",
              "Constitutional republic",
              "Parliament republic",
              "Parliament monarchy"
            ],
            "explaination": "The laws passed after the Glorious Revolution are the beginning of what is called ‘constitutional monarchy’. The monarch remained very important but was no longer able to insist on particular policies or actions if Parliament did not agree."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "The right for women to vote",
            "id": "T10-18",
            "level": 3.4,
            "question": "What did Emmeline Pankhurst fight for?",
            "options": [
              "Freedom of expression",
              "Prohibition of slavery and forced labour",
              "The right for women to vote",
              "The right to liberty and security"
            ],
            "explaination": "Emmeline Pankhurst was born in Manchester in 1858. She set up the Women’s Franchise League in 1889, which fought to get the vote in local elections for married women. In 1903 she helped found the Women’s Social and Political Union (WSPU). This was the first group whose members were called ‘suffragettes’. The group used civil disobedience as part of their protest to gain the vote for women."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "A period when new ideas about politics, philosophy and science were developed",
            "id": "T11-05",
            "level": 3.4,
            "question": "What is the Enlightenment?",
            "options": [
              "A period of total peace in England",
              "A period when England became the largest empire the world had ever seen",
              "A period when new ideas about politics, philosophy and science were developed",
              "A period of economic recovery after the Second World War"
            ],
            "explaination": "During the 18th century, new ideas about politics, philosophy and science were developed. This is often called ‘the Enlightenment’."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "A suffragette",
            "id": "T11-22",
            "level": 3.4,
            "question": "Who was Emmeline Pankhurst?",
            "options": [
              "A nurse",
              "A scientist",
              "A suffragette",
              "The Prime Minister"
            ],
            "explaination": "Emmeline Pankhurst was born in Manchester in 1858. She set up the Women’s Franchise League in 1889, which fought to get the vote in local elections for married women. In 1903 she helped found the Women’s Social and Political Union (WSPU). This was the first group whose members were called ‘suffragettes’. The group used civil disobedience as part of their protest to gain the vote for women."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Russia",
            "id": "T11-23",
            "level": 3.4,
            "question": "Who did Britain fight against in the Crimean War?",
            "options": [
              "France",
              "Germany",
              "Turkey",
              "Russia"
            ],
            "explaination": "From 1853 to 1856, Britain fought with Turkey and France against Russia in the Crimean War. It was the first war to be extensively covered by the media through news stories and photographs."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Admiral Nelson",
            "id": "T12-04",
            "level": 3.4,
            "question": "Who was in charge of the British fleet at the Battle of Trafalgar?",
            "options": [
              "The Duke of Wellington",
              "Admiral Nelson",
              "Robert the Bruce",
              "Oliver Cromwell"
            ],
            "explaination": "Britain’s navy fought against combined French and Spanish fleets, winning the Battle of Trafalgar in 1805. Admiral Nelson was in charge of the British fleet at Trafalgar and was killed in the battle. "
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "France",
            "id": "T12-10",
            "level": 3.4,
            "question": "Between 1680 and 1720 many refugees called Huguenots came to England, which country did they come from?",
            "options": [
              "Pakistan",
              "France",
              "India",
              "China"
            ],
            "explaination": "Between 1680 and 1720 many refugees called Huguenots came from France. They were Protestants and had been persecuted for their religion. Many were educated and skilled and worked as scientists, in banking, or in weaving or other crafts."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "The flag of the United Kingdom",
            "id": "T12-22",
            "level": 3.4,
            "question": "What is the Union Jack?",
            "options": [
              "The flag of the Commonwealth",
              "The shield used by British Knights",
              "The flag of the United Kingdom",
              "The flag of the European Union"
            ],
            "explaination": "One symbol of the union between England, Scotland, Wales and Ireland was a new version of the official flag, the Union Flag. This is often called the Union Jack. The flag combined crosses associated with England, Scotland and Ireland. It is still used today as the official flag of the UK."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Highlands",
            "id": "T13-10",
            "level": 3.4,
            "question": "During the rebellion of the clans in Scotland, Bonnie Prince Charlie was supported by clansmen from which Scottish region?",
            "options": [
              "Glasgow",
              "Edinburgh",
              "Galloway",
              "Highlands"
            ],
            "explaination": "Charles Edward Stuart (Bonnie Prince Charlie), the grandson of James II, landed in Scotland. He was supported by clansmen from the Scottish highlands and raised an army."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "France",
            "id": "T13-16",
            "level": 3.4,
            "question": "Against which country did Britain fight at the Battle of Waterloo?",
            "options": [
              "Italy",
              "Spain",
              "Germany",
              "France"
            ],
            "explaination": "The British army also fought against the French. In 1815, the French Wars ended with the defeat of the Emperor Napoleon by the Duke of Wellington at the Battle of Waterloo."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "A politician",
            "id": "T13-17",
            "level": 3.4,
            "question": "Who was William Wilberforce?",
            "options": [
              "A sportsman",
              "An artist",
              "A poet",
              "A politician"
            ],
            "explaination": "William Wilberforce, an evangelical Christian and a member of Parliament, also played an important part in changing the law. Along with other abolitionists (people who supported the abolition of slavery), he succeeded in turning public opinion against the slave trade."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Sir Robert Walpole",
            "id": "T14-03",
            "level": 3.4,
            "question": "Who was the first British Prime Minister?",
            "options": [
              "Winston Churchill",
              "Sir Robert Walpole",
              "Clement Atlee",
              "R A Butler"
            ],
            "explaination": "The most important minister in Parliament became known as the Prime Minister. The first man to be called this was Sir Robert Walpole, who was Prime Minister from 1721 to 1742."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Economics",
            "id": "T14-05",
            "level": 3.4,
            "question": "During the Enlightenment, Adam Smith developed ideas about:",
            "options": [
              "Science",
              "Economics",
              "Philosophy",
              "Politics"
            ],
            "explaination": "Adam Smith developed ideas about economics which are still referred to today. David Hume’s ideas about human nature continue to influence philosophers. Scientific discoveries, such as James Watt’s work on steam power, helped the progress of the Industrial Revolution."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Admiral Nelson",
            "id": "T14-06",
            "level": 3.4,
            "question": "Who died at the Battle of Trafalgar?",
            "options": [
              "Napoleon",
              "Admiral Nelson",
              "Oliver Cromwell",
              "Duke of Wellington"
            ],
            "explaination": "Napoleon, who became Emperor of France, continued the war. Britain’s navy fought against combined French and Spanish fleets, winning the Battle of Trafalgar in 1805. Admiral Nelson was in charge of the British fleet at Trafalgar and was killed in the battle."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "James Cook",
            "id": "T14-11",
            "level": 3.4,
            "question": "Who mapped the coast of Australia?",
            "options": [
              "Admiral Nelson",
              "James Cook",
              "Sake Dean Mahomet",
              "Richard Arkwright"
            ],
            "explaination": "Captain James Cook mapped the coast of Australia and a few colonies were established there."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "The Crimean War",
            "id": "T14-12",
            "level": 3.4,
            "question": "What was the first war to be extensively covered by the media?",
            "options": [
              "The Crimean War",
              "The Boer War",
              "The First World War",
              "The Second World War"
            ],
            "explaination": "From 1853 to 1856, Britain fought with Turkey and France against Russia in the Crimean War. It was the first war to be extensively covered by the media through news stories and photographs."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "To link the factories to towns and cities and to the ports",
            "id": "T14-20",
            "level": 3.4,
            "question": "Why were canals built during the Industrial Revolution?",
            "options": [
              "To make space for the large fleet of British ships",
              "To link the factories to towns and cities and to the ports",
              "To increase the amount of water in towns and cities",
              "To increase the number of water mills in the UK"
            ],
            "explaination": "Better transport links were needed to transport raw materials and manufactured goods. Canals were built to link the factories to towns and cities and to the ports, particularly in the new industrial areas in the middle and north of England."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Steam power",
            "id": "T14-23",
            "level": 3.4,
            "question": "Which invention led to the development of Britain during the Industrial Revolution?",
            "options": [
              "Radar",
              "Bessemer process",
              "Steam power",
              "Hovercraft"
            ],
            "explaination": "Scientific discoveries, such as James Watt’s work on steam power, helped the progress of the Industrial Revolution."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "North American",
            "id": "T15-02",
            "level": 3.4,
            "question": "In 1776, which British colonies declared their independence because they demanded that there should be ‘no taxation without representation’.",
            "options": [
              "North African",
              "North American",
              "South African",
              "Australia"
            ],
            "explaination": "By the 1760s, there were substantial British colonies in North America. The colonies were wealthy and largely in control of their own affairs. Many of the colonist families had originally gone to North America in order to have religious freedom. They were well educated and interested in ideas of liberty. The British government wanted to tax the colonies. The colonists saw this as an attack on their freedom and said there should be ‘no taxation without representation’ in the British Parliament."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Auld Lang Syne",
            "id": "T15-13",
            "level": 3.4,
            "question": "What song is sung by people in the UK and other countries when they are celebrating the New Year?",
            "options": [
              "The British Anthem",
              "Auld Lang Syne",
              "Home Thoughts from Abroad",
              "Anthem for Doomed Youth"
            ],
            "explaination": "The song Auld Lang Syne, which is sung by people in the UK and other countries when they are celebrating the New Year (or Hogmanay as it is called in Scotland)."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Fenians",
            "id": "T15-17",
            "level": 3.4,
            "question": "What is the name of Irish people who favoured complete independence from the UK in the 19th century?",
            "options": [
              "Protestant",
              "Fenians",
              "Suffragettes",
              "Gentry"
            ],
            "explaination": "The Irish Nationalist movement had grown strongly through the 19th century. Some, such as the Fenians, favoured complete independence."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "1833",
            "id": "T15-21",
            "level": 3.4,
            "question": "When did the Emancipation Act abolish slavery throughout the British Empire?",
            "options": [
              "1807",
              "1812",
              "1833",
              "1851"
            ],
            "explaination": "In 1807, it became illegal to trade slaves in British ships or from British ports, and in 1833 the Emancipation Act abolished slavery throughout the British Empire."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "The construction of the Great Western Railway.",
            "id": "T16-20",
            "level": 3.4,
            "question": "Isambard Kingdom Brunel was responsible for:",
            "options": [
              "The invention of the radar.",
              "The invention of the steam engine.",
              "The construction of the Tower of London.",
              "The construction of the Great Western Railway."
            ],
            "explaination": "Isambard Kingdom Brunel (1806–59) was originally from Portsmouth, England. He was an engineer who built tunnels, bridges, railway lines and ships. He was responsible for constructing the Great Western Railway, which was the first major railway built in Britain."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Philosophy",
            "id": "T17-15",
            "level": 3.4,
            "question": "During the 18th century the Enlightenment, which aspect was David Hume's contribution?",
            "options": [
              "Science",
              "Economics",
              "Philosophy",
              "Politics"
            ],
            "explaination": "David Hume’s ideas about human nature continue to influence philosophers."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Opened first curry house",
            "id": "T17-19",
            "level": 3.4,
            "question": "Who was Sake Dean Mahomet?",
            "options": [
              "Opened first curry house",
              "Opened first florist",
              "Opened first spice shop",
              "Opened first pet shop"
            ],
            "explaination": "Sake Dean Mahomet (1759–1851) was born in 1759 and grew up in the Bengal region of India. In 1810 he opened the Hindoostane Coffee House in George Street, London. It was the first curry house to open in Britain. Mahomet and his wife also introduced ‘shampooing’, the Indian art of head massage, to Britain."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "A new law limited the number of hours women and children could work",
            "id": "T17-20",
            "level": 3.4,
            "question": "How was the working condition improved for women and children in 1847?",
            "options": [
              "Transportation network is improved",
              "The wages is increased",
              "A new law limited the number of hours women and children could work",
              "A better accommodation is provided"
            ],
            "explaination": "Working conditions in factories gradually became better. In 1847, the number of hours that women and children could work was limited by law to 10 hours per day. Better housing began to be built for workers."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Prime Minister",
            "id": "T17-23",
            "level": 3.4,
            "question": "During 18 Century, an important role appeared in the parliament?",
            "options": [
              "Judge",
              "Prime Minister",
              "The Speaker",
              "The cabinet"
            ],
            "explaination": "The most important minister in Parliament became known as the Prime Minister. The first man to be called this was Sir Robert Walpole, who was Prime Minister from 1721 to 1742."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Potato",
            "id": "T17-24",
            "level": 3.4,
            "question": "During 1840s, which crop was affected by a disease causing Ireland suffered from famine?",
            "options": [
              "Bailey",
              "Wheat",
              "Potato",
              "Corn"
            ],
            "explaination": "In the middle of the century the potato crop failed, and Ireland suffered a famine. A million people died from disease and starvation."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Agriculture",
            "id": "T17-34",
            "level": 3.4,
            "question": "Before the 18th century, what was the biggest source of employment?",
            "options": [
              "Aircraft industry",
              "Manufacturing",
              "Agriculture",
              "Mining"
            ],
            "explaination": "Before the 18th century, agriculture was the biggest source of employment in Britain. There were many cottage industries, where people worked from home to produce goods such as cloth and lace. The Industrial Revolution was the rapid development of industry in Britain in the 18th and 19th centuries. Manufacturing jobs became the main source of employment in Britain."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Constructing the railway and bridge.",
            "id": "T17-38",
            "level": 3.4,
            "question": "What was Isambard Kingdom Brunel responsible for?",
            "options": [
              "Constructing Clifton Suspension Bridge.",
              "Constructing the railway and bridge.",
              "Constructing the Tower of London.",
              "Constructing Big Ben."
            ],
            "explaination": "Isambard Kingdom Brunel (1806–59) was originally from Portsmouth, England. He was an engineer who built tunnels, bridges, railway lines and ships. He was responsible for constructing the Great Western Railway, which was the first major railway built in Britain."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Constitutional monarchy",
            "id": "T17-39",
            "level": 3.4,
            "question": "What is the name, after the Glorious Revolution, the monarch was no longer able to insist on particular policies or actions if parliamentary did not agree.",
            "options": [
              "Constitutional monarchy",
              "Constitutional republic",
              "Parliament republic",
              "Parliament monarchy"
            ],
            "explaination": "The laws passed after the Glorious Revolution are the beginning of what is called ‘constitutional monarchy’. The monarch remained very important but was no longer able to insist on particular policies or actions if Parliament did not agree."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Prime Minister",
            "id": "T17-40",
            "level": 3.4,
            "question": "During 18 Century, an important post appeared in the parliament, Sir Robert Walpole taken that post.",
            "options": [
              "Judge",
              "Prime Minister",
              "The Speaker",
              "The cabinet"
            ],
            "explaination": "The most important minister in Parliament became known as the Prime Minister. The first man to be called this was Sir Robert Walpole, who was Prime Minister from 1721 to 1742."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "The First World War",
            "id": "T2-05",
            "level": 3.4,
            "question": "Women over the age of 30 were given the right to vote as a result of their contribution towards the war effort. Which war was that?",
            "options": [
              "The First World War",
              "The Second World War",
              "The Civil War",
              "The Crimean War"
            ],
            "explaination": "In 1918, women over the age of 30 were given voting rights and the right to stand for Parliament, partly in recognition of the contribution women made to the war effort during the First World War."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Bonnie Prince Charlie",
            "id": "T3-06",
            "level": 3.4,
            "question": "Who was supported by clansmen from the Scottish highlands and raised and army in 1745?",
            "options": [
              "Kenneth MacAlpin",
              "Oliver Cromwell",
              "Robert Burns",
              "Bonnie Prince Charlie"
            ],
            "explaination": "In 1745 there was another attempt to put a Stuart king back on the throne in place of George I’s son, George II. Charles Edward Stuart (Bonnie Prince Charlie), the grandson of James II, landed in Scotland. He was supported by clansmen from the Scottish highlands and raised and army."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "The British government wanted to tax them",
            "id": "T3-18",
            "level": 3.4,
            "question": "What led the American colonies to want their independence from Britain?",
            "options": [
              "They were running out of resources",
              "The British government wanted to control their borders",
              "There were not enough jobs for the local people",
              "The British government wanted to tax them"
            ],
            "explaination": " The British government wanted to tax the colonies. The colonists saw this as an attack on their freedom and said there should be ‘no taxation without representation’ in the British Parliament."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Emmeline Pankhurst",
            "id": "T3-20",
            "level": 3.4,
            "question": "Who was the leader of the suffragettes, the group that campaigned for women’s rights to vote?",
            "options": [
              "Mary Peters",
              "Margaret Thatcher",
              "Emmeline Pankhurst",
              "Florence Nightingale"
            ],
            "explaination": "Emmeline Pankhurst was born in Manchester in 1858. She set up the Women’s Franchise League in 1889, which fought to get the vote in local elections for married women. In 1903 she helped found the Women’s Social and Political Union (WSPU). This was the first group whose members were called ‘suffragettes’."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "The Battle of Waterloo",
            "id": "T4-01",
            "level": 3.4,
            "question": "What was the last battle between Great Britain and France?",
            "options": [
              "The Battle of Hastings",
              "The Battle of Trafalgar",
              "The Battle of Waterloo",
              "Battle of Agincourt"
            ],
            "explaination": " The British army also fought against the French. In 1815, the French Wars ended with the defeat of the Emperor Napoleon by the Duke of Wellington at the Battle of Waterloo."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "1928",
            "id": "T4-11",
            "level": 3.4,
            "question": "When did women get the right to vote at the same age as men?",
            "options": [
              "1918",
              "1928",
              "1948",
              "1969"
            ],
            "explaination": "The voting franchise was also extended to women over 30, and then in 1928 to men and women over 21."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "The Enlightenment",
            "id": "T5-14",
            "level": 3.4,
            "question": "What is the name of the period when new ideas about politics, philosophy and science were developed?",
            "options": [
              "The Glorious Revolution",
              "The Enlightenment",
              "The Reformation",
              "The Swinging Sixties"
            ],
            "explaination": "During the 18th century, new ideas about politics, philosophy and science were developed. This is often called ‘the Enlightenment’."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "The Battle of Trafalgar",
            "id": "T5-17",
            "level": 3.4,
            "question": "In which battle did Admiral Nelson die?",
            "options": [
              "The Battle of Bannockburn",
              "The Battle of Hastings",
              "The Battle of Waterloo",
              "The Battle of Trafalgar"
            ],
            "explaination": "Admiral Nelson was in charge of the British fleet at Trafalgar and was killed in the battle."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "South Africa",
            "id": "T5-21",
            "level": 3.4,
            "question": "In which country of the British Empire did the Boer War (1899-1902) take place?",
            "options": [
              "South Africa",
              "Netherlands",
              "France",
              "Germany"
            ],
            "explaination": "The Boer War of 1899 to 1902 made the discussions about the future of the Empire more urgent. The British went to war in South Africa with settlers from the Netherlands called the Boers."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "False",
            "id": "T7-03",
            "level": 3.4,
            "question": "The Bill of Rights in 1689 gave women the right to vote.",
            "options": [
              "True",
              "False"
            ],
            "explaination": " The Bill of Rights, 1689, confirmed the rights of Parliament and the limits of the king’s power."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Manufacturing",
            "id": "T7-05",
            "level": 3.4,
            "question": "What was the biggest source of employment during the 18th century?",
            "options": [
              "Aircraft industry",
              "Manufacturing",
              "Agriculture",
              "Mining"
            ],
            "explaination": "Before the 18th century, agriculture was the biggest source of employment in Britain. There were many cottage industries, where people worked from home to produce goods such as cloth and lace. The Industrial Revolution was the rapid development of industry in Britain in the 18th and 19th centuries. Manufacturing jobs became the main source of employment in Britain."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "True",
            "id": "T7-12",
            "level": 3.4,
            "question": "In 1833 the Emancipation Act abolished slavery throughout the British Empire.",
            "options": [
              "True",
              "False"
            ],
            "explaination": ""
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "The Highland Clearances",
            "id": "T7-13",
            "level": 3.4,
            "question": "What is the name of the process by which many Scottish landlords destroyed individual small farms (known as ‘crofts’) to make space for large flocks of sheep and cattle?",
            "options": [
              "The Enlightenment",
              "The Black Death",
              "Glorious Revolution",
              "The Highland Clearances"
            ],
            "explaination": "A process began which became known as the ‘Highland Clearances’. Many Scottish landlords destroyed individual small farms (known as ‘crofts’) to make space for large flocks of sheep and cattle."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Suffragettes",
            "id": "T7-16",
            "level": 3.4,
            "question": "What was the name of the activist group who fought for the women’s right to vote?",
            "options": [
              "Protestant",
              "Fenians",
              "Beefeaters",
              "Suffragettes"
            ],
            "explaination": "Emmeline Pankhurst set up the Women’s Franchise League in 1889, which fought to get the vote in local elections for married women. In 1903 she helped found the Women’s Social and Political Union (WSPU). This was the first group whose members were called ‘suffragettes’. The group used civil disobedience as part of their protest to gain the vote for women."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "1918",
            "id": "T8-16",
            "level": 3.4,
            "question": "What year were women given the right to vote?",
            "options": [
              "1918",
              "1928",
              "1948",
              "1968"
            ],
            "explaination": "In 1918, women over the age of 30 were given voting rights and the right to stand for Parliament, partly in recognition of the contribution women made to the war effort during the First World War. Shortly before Emmeline’s death in 1928, women were given the right to vote at the age of 21, the same as men."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "False",
            "id": "T9-02",
            "level": 3.4,
            "question": "The last battle between Britain and France was the battle of Trafalgar.",
            "options": [
              "True",
              "False"
            ],
            "explaination": "In 1815, the French Wars ended with the defeat of the Emperor Napoleon by the Duke of Wellington at the Battle of Waterloo."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Women were given the right to vote at the age of 21, the same as men.",
            "id": "T9-07",
            "level": 3.4,
            "question": "Why is 1928 an important year in women’s voting history?",
            "options": [
              "Women were given the right to vote at the age of 18, the same as men.",
              "Women were given the right to vote at the age of 25.",
              "Women were given the right to vote at the age of 30.",
              "Women were given the right to vote at the age of 21, the same as men."
            ],
            "explaination": "The voting franchise was also extended to women over 30, and then in 1928 to men and women over 21. In 1969, the voting age was reduced to 18 for men and women."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "The Boer War",
            "id": "T9-10",
            "level": 3.4,
            "question": "Which of the following wars took place between 1899 and 1902 in South Africa?",
            "options": [
              "The Crimean War",
              "The Boer War",
              "The Hundred Years War",
              "The First World War"
            ],
            "explaination": "The Boer War of 1899 to 1902 made the discussions about the future of the Empire more urgent. The British went to war in South Africa with settlers from the Netherlands called the Boers."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Abolishing a number of taxes on imported goods",
            "id": "T9-14",
            "level": 3.4,
            "question": "How did the Government promote policies of free trade during the Victorian Age?",
            "options": [
              "Preventing the importation of cheap raw materials",
              "Preventing the importation of cheap grain",
              "Abolishing a number of taxes on imported goods",
              "Abolishing the exportation of local produce"
            ],
            "explaination": "Britain continued to be a great trading nation. The government began to promote policies of free trade, abolishing a number of taxes on imported goods."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "A British officer in charge of the British fleet at the Battle of Trafalgar against the Spanish fleet",
            "id": "T9-15",
            "level": 3.4,
            "question": "Who was Admiral Nelson?",
            "options": [
              "A British general who established the authority of the English Parliament",
              "A British officer in charge of the British fleet at the Battle of Trafalgar against the Spanish fleet",
              "A British officer in charge of the British army at the Battle of Waterloo",
              "One of the tribal leaders who fought against the Romans"
            ],
            "explaination": "Britain’s navy fought against combined French and Spanish fleets, winning the Battle of Trafalgar in 1805. Admiral Nelson was in charge of the British fleet at Trafalgar and was killed in the battle."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "The Steam Power",
            "id": "T9-17",
            "level": 3.4,
            "question": "Which invention lead to the rapid development of the industry in Britain during the 18th and 19th centuries?",
            "options": [
              "The Jet Engine",
              "The Radar",
              "The Steam Power",
              "Bessemer process"
            ],
            "explaination": "The Industrial Revolution was the rapid development of industry in Britain in the 18th and 19th centuries. Britain was the first country to industrialise on a large scale. It happened because of the development of machinery and the use of steam power."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "The Crystal Palace",
            "id": "T9-23",
            "level": 3.4,
            "question": "What building was constructed in Hyde Park to hold the Great Exhibition of 1851?",
            "options": [
              "Buckingham Palace",
              "The Crystal Palace",
              "Palace of Westminster",
              "The Royal Albert Hall"
            ],
            "explaination": "In 1851, the Great Exhibition opened in Hyde Park in the Crystal Palace, a huge building made of steel and glass."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "A nurse",
            "id": "T9-24",
            "level": 3.4,
            "question": "Who was Florence Nightingale?",
            "options": [
              "A poet",
              "An economist",
              "A nurse",
              "A politician"
            ],
            "explaination": "Florence Nightingale was born in Italy to English parents. At the age of 31, she trained as a nurse in Germany."
          }
        ]
    },
    {
        "category": "3.5 The 20th century",
        "questions":
        [
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "In 1918",
            "id": "T10-21",
            "level": 3.5,
            "question": "When did the WWI come to an end?",
            "options": [
              "In 1914",
              "In 1918",
              "In 1939",
              "In 1943"
            ],
            "explaination": "On 28 June 1914, Archduke Franz Ferdinand of Austria was assassinated. This set off a chain of events leading to the First World War (1914–18)."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "The Battle of Britain",
            "id": "T11-07",
            "level": 3.5,
            "question": "Which of the following was a crucial aerial battle fought between Germany and Britain during WWII?",
            "options": [
              "Battle of Waterloo",
              "The Battle of Marston Moor",
              "The Battle of Britain",
              "Battle of Trafalgar"
            ],
            "explaination": "Hitler wanted to invade Britain, but before sending in troops, Germany needed to control the air. The Germans waged an air campaign against Britain, but the British resisted with their fighter planes and eventually won the crucial aerial battle against the Germans, called ‘the Battle of Britain’, in the summer of 1940."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "The evacuation of Allied soldiers from France during World War II",
            "id": "T12-17",
            "level": 3.5,
            "question": "What is known as the “Dunkirk spirit”?",
            "options": [
              "When new social classes appeared after the Black Death",
              "The evacuation of Allied soldiers from France during World War II",
              "When the German air force bombed London and other British cities at night-time",
              "The period when many refugees called Huguenots came from France"
            ],
            "explaination": "As France fell, the British decided to evacuate British and French soldiers from France in a huge naval operation. Many civilian volunteers in small pleasure and fishing boats from Britain helped the Navy to rescue more than 300,000 men from the beaches around Dunkirk. Although many lives and a lot of equipment were lost, the evacuation was a success and meant that Britain was better able to continue the fight against the Germans. The evacuation gave rise to the phrase ‘the Dunkirk spirit’."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "The Royal Air Force",
            "id": "T13-13",
            "level": 3.5,
            "question": "Which armed force was used in the Battle of Britain?",
            "options": [
              "The Royal Navy",
              "The Royal Air Force",
              "The Naval Service",
              "The Police Force"
            ],
            "explaination": "Hitler wanted to invade Britain, but before sending in troops, Germany needed to control the air. The Germans waged an air campaign against Britain, but the British resisted with their fighter planes and eventually won the crucial aerial battle against the Germans, called ‘the Battle of Britain’, in the summer of 1940. The most important planes used by the Royal Air Force in the Battle of Britain were the Spitfire and the Hurricane – which were designed and built in Britain."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "At 11.00 am on 11th November 1918",
            "id": "T15-06",
            "level": 3.5,
            "question": "When did the First World War end?",
            "options": [
              "At 12.00 pm on 11th November 1918",
              "At 12.00 pm on 11th November 1928",
              "At 11.00 am on 11th November 1918",
              "At 11.00 am on 11th November 1928"
            ],
            "explaination": "The First World War ended at 11.00 am on 11th November 1918 with victory for Britain and its allies."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Ernest Rutherford",
            "id": "T15-12",
            "level": 3.5,
            "question": "Who led a team of scientists to ‘split the atom’ for the first time?",
            "options": [
              "James Watt",
              "Ernest Rutherford",
              "Alexander Fleming",
              "Sir Robert Watson-Watt"
            ],
            "explaination": "Scientists led by Ernest Rutherford, working at Manchester and then Cambridge University, were the first to ‘split the atom’ and took part in the Manhattan Project in the United States, which developed the atomic bomb."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "The Blitz",
            "id": "T17-09",
            "level": 3.5,
            "question": "What is the name used to describe the bombing campaign during WWII when Germany bombed multiple UK cities？",
            "options": [
              "Canvassing",
              "Proms",
              "Fenians",
              "The Blitz"
            ],
            "explaination": "The German air force was able to continue bombing London and other British cities at night-time. This was called the Blitz."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "1949",
            "id": "T2-06",
            "level": 3.5,
            "question": "When did Ireland become a republic?",
            "options": [
              "1929",
              "1939",
              "1949",
              "1969"
            ],
            "explaination": "Ireland became a republic in 1949."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Winston Churchill",
            "id": "T2-09",
            "level": 3.5,
            "question": "Who became Prime Minister and was an inspirational leader to the British people during WWII?",
            "options": [
              "Clement Attlee",
              "Sir Robert Walpole",
              "Winston Churchill",
              "Margaret Thatcher"
            ],
            "explaination": "Churchill was the son of a politician and, before becoming a Conservative MP in 1900, was a soldier and journalist. In May 1940 he became Prime Minister. He refused to surrender to the Nazis and was an inspirational leader to the British people in a time of great hardship."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Shipbuilding",
            "id": "T3-22",
            "level": 3.5,
            "question": "During the Great Depression in the 1930s which industry was badly affected?",
            "options": [
              "Aviation",
              "Automobile",
              "Shipbuilding",
              "Housing construction"
            ],
            "explaination": "The effects of the depression of the 1930s were felt differently in different parts of the UK. The traditional heavy industries such as shipbuilding were badly affected but new industries – including the automobile and aviation industries – developed."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Winston Churchill",
            "id": "T4-09",
            "level": 3.5,
            "question": "Who was voted the greatest Briton of all time in 2002?",
            "options": [
              "Sir Steve Redgrave",
              "Margaret Thatcher",
              "William Shakespeare",
              "Winston Churchill"
            ],
            "explaination": "Winston Churchill was an MP until he stood down at the 1964 General Election. Following his death in 1965, he was given a state funeral. He remains a much-admired figure to this day, and in 2002 was voted the greatest Briton of all time by the public."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "1939",
            "id": "T5-24",
            "level": 3.5,
            "question": "When did Germany invade Poland?",
            "options": [
              "1939",
              "1940",
              "1941",
              "1942"
            ],
            "explaination": "when Hitler invaded Poland in 1939, Britain and France declared war in order to stop his aggression."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "An aerial battle",
            "id": "T6-14",
            "level": 3.5,
            "question": "What sort of battle was the ‘Battle of Britain’, fought between Germany and Britain in the summer of 1940?",
            "options": [
              "A battle without rifles",
              "An aerial battle",
              "A battle in the sea",
              "A battle in the mountains"
            ],
            "explaination": "Hitler wanted to invade Britain, but before sending in troops, Germany needed to control the air. The Germans waged an air campaign against Britain, but the British resisted with their fighter planes and eventually won the crucial aerial battle against the Germans, called ‘the Battle of Britain’, in the summer of 1940."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Due to the outbreak of the First World War",
            "id": "T6-22",
            "level": 3.5,
            "question": "In 1913, the British government promised ‘Home Rule’ for Ireland, why were changes in Ireland delayed until 1921?",
            "options": [
              "Due to the outbreak of the Black Death",
              "Due to the outbreak of the First World War",
              "Due to the outbreak of the Second World War",
              "Because there was not a king on the British throne"
            ],
            "explaination": "In 1913, the British government promised ‘Home Rule’ for Ireland. The proposal was to have a self-governing Ireland with its own parliament but still part of the UK. A Home Rule Bill was introduced in Parliament. It was opposed by the Protestants in the north of Ireland, who threatened to resist Home Rule by force. The outbreak of the First World War led the British government to postpone any changes in Ireland."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "The First World War",
            "id": "T7-10",
            "level": 3.5,
            "question": "The assassination of the Archduke Franz Ferdinand of Austria in 1914 led to which of the following wars?",
            "options": [
              "The Civil War",
              "The First World War",
              "The Second World War",
              "The Crimean War"
            ],
            "explaination": "On 28 June 1914, Archduke Franz Ferdinand of Austria was assassinated. This set off a chain of events leading to the First World War (1914–18)"
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Poland",
            "id": "T8-01",
            "level": 3.5,
            "question": "World War II started as a result of Germany invading which country?",
            "options": [
              "Russia",
              "Poland",
              "France",
              "America"
            ],
            "explaination": "When Hitler invaded Poland in 1939, Britain and France declared war in order to stop his aggression."
          }
        ]
    },
    {
        "category": "3.6 Britain since 1945",
        "questions":
        [
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Margaret Thatcher",
            "id": "T1-09",
            "level": 3.6,
            "question": "Who was the first female Prime Minister of the UK?",
            "options": [
              "Theresa May",
              "Margaret Thatcher",
              "Mary Stuart",
              "Florence Nightingale"
            ],
            "explaination": "Margaret Thatcher was the first woman Prime Minister of the UK."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Jet engine",
            "id": "T1-21",
            "level": 3.6,
            "question": "What did Sir Frank Whittle invent in the 1930s?",
            "options": [
              "Radar",
              "Steam engine",
              "Jet engine",
              "Hovercraft"
            ],
            "explaination": "The jet engine was developed in Britain in the 1930s by Sir Frank Whittle."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "She was the first woman Prime Minister of the UK",
            "id": "T11-08",
            "level": 3.6,
            "question": "What was Margaret Thatcher famous for?",
            "options": [
              "She was the founder of modern nursing",
              "She set up the women’s Franchise League",
              "She fought for the right to vote for women",
              "She was the first woman Prime Minister of the UK"
            ],
            "explaination": "Margaret Thatcher, Britain’s first woman Prime Minister, led the Conservative government from 1979 to 1990."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "A growth in British fashion and pop music",
            "id": "T12-09",
            "level": 3.6,
            "question": "What is the period of the 1960s known for?",
            "options": [
              "Demand more political power",
              "A growth in British fashion and pop music",
              "Working conditions in factories gradually became better.",
              " It was a time when Britain increased in power and influence abroad."
            ],
            "explaination": "The decade of the 1960s was a period of significant social change. It was known as ‘the Swinging Sixties’. There was growth in British fashion, cinema and popular music."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Sir Tim Berners-Lee",
            "id": "T12-15",
            "level": 3.6,
            "question": "Who invented the World Wide Web?",
            "options": [
              "Sir Robert Edwards",
              "Sir Christopher Cockerell",
              "Sir Frank Whittle",
              "Sir Tim Berners-Lee"
            ],
            "explaination": "The inventor of the World Wide Web, Sir Tim Berners-Lee (1955–), is British. Information was successfully transferred via the web for the first time on 25 December 1990."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Clement Attlee",
            "id": "T14-18",
            "level": 3.6,
            "question": "Who was elected as British Prime Minister in 1945?",
            "options": [
              "Clement Attlee",
              "Sir Robert Walpole",
              "Winston Churchill",
              "Margaret Thatcher"
            ],
            "explaination": "In 1945 the British people elected a Labour government. The new Prime Minister was Clement Atlee, who promised to introduce the welfare state outlined in the Beveridge Report."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "France",
            "id": "T14-22",
            "level": 3.6,
            "question": "Which of the following countries helped Britain to develop the Concorde?",
            "options": [
              "Germany",
              "France",
              "Italy",
              "Spain"
            ],
            "explaination": "The 1960s was also a time of technological progress. Britain and France developed the world’s only supersonic commercial airliner, Concorde."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Gold",
            "id": "T15-08",
            "level": 3.6,
            "question": "What medal did Mary Peters win in the 1972 Olympics?",
            "options": [
              "Bronze",
              "Silver",
              "Gold",
              "No medal"
            ],
            "explaination": "Mary Peters (1939–) born in Manchester, Mary Peters moved to Northern Ireland as a child. She was a talented athlete who won an Olympic gold medal in the pentathlon in 1972."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "The Turing machine",
            "id": "T15-10",
            "level": 3.6,
            "question": "What was invented by Alan Turing in the 1930s?",
            "options": [
              "The steam engine",
              "The Turing machine",
              "The television",
              "The jet engine"
            ],
            "explaination": "A Turing machine is a theoretical mathematical device invented by Alan Turing (1912–54), a British mathematician, in the 1930s."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "The Rolling Stones;The Beatles",
            "id": "T15-18",
            "level": 3.6,
            "question": "Which two British pop music groups were famous during the Swinging Sixties?",
            "options": [
              "Queen",
              "The Rolling Stones",
              "The Beatles",
              "Coldplay"
            ],
            "explaination": "Two well-known pop music groups at the time were The Beatles and The Rolling Stones."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Francis Crick",
            "id": "T16-10",
            "level": 3.6,
            "question": "Who was the British scientist who co-discovered the structure of the DNA molecule in the 1950s?",
            "options": [
              "Sir Frank Whittle",
              "Francis Crick",
              "Sir Peter Mansfield",
              "John MacLeod"
            ],
            "explaination": "The structure of the DNA molecule was discovered in 1953 through work at British universities in London and Cambridge. Francis Crick (1916–2004), one of those awarded the Nobel Prize for this discovery, was British."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Tony Blair",
            "id": "T16-13",
            "level": 3.6,
            "question": "Who was the leader of the Labour Party who introduced a Scottish Parliament and a Welsh Assembly?",
            "options": [
              "Clement Atlee",
              "Tony Blair",
              "William Beveridge",
              "R A Butler"
            ],
            "explaination": "In 1997 the Labour Party led by Tony Blair was elected. The Blair government introduced a Scottish Parliament and a Welsh Assembly."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "John Major",
            "id": "T16-16",
            "level": 3.6,
            "question": "Who became Prime Minister after Margaret Thatcher and played an important part in the Northern Ireland peace process?",
            "options": [
              "Tony Blair",
              "John Major",
              "Sir Robert Walpole",
              "Winston Churchill"
            ],
            "explaination": "John Major was Prime Minister after Mrs Thatcher, and helped establish the Northern Ireland peace process."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Margaret Thatcher",
            "id": "T17-06",
            "level": 3.6,
            "question": "Who was the longest-serving Prime Minister of the 20th century?",
            "options": [
              "John Major",
              "Tony Blair",
              "Sir Robert Walpole",
              "Margaret Thatcher"
            ],
            "explaination": "Margaret Thatcher, Britain’s first woman Prime Minister, led the Conservative government from 1979 to 1990. She was the longest-serving Prime Minister of the 20th century, remaining in Office until 1990."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Television",
            "id": "T2-24",
            "level": 3.6,
            "question": "What did the Scottish John Logie Baird develop?",
            "options": [
              "Radar",
              "Jet engine",
              "Radio",
              "Television"
            ],
            "explaination": "The television was developed by Scotsman John Logie Baird in the 1920s."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Britain;France",
            "id": "T3-10",
            "level": 3.6,
            "question": "Which two countries developed the Concorde, the world’s only supersonic commercial airliner?",
            "options": [
              "Britain",
              "Italy",
              "Germany",
              "France"
            ],
            "explaination": "Britain and France developed the world’s only supersonic commercial airliner, Concorde."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Sir Robert Watson-Watt",
            "id": "T4-22",
            "level": 3.6,
            "question": "Who developed the radar?",
            "options": [
              "James Watt",
              "Sir Robert Watson-Watt",
              "John Logie Baird",
              "Francis Crick"
            ],
            "explaination": "Radar was developed by Scotsman Sir Robert Watson-Watt (1892–1973), who proposed that enemy aircraft could be detected by radio waves."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "The structure of the DNA molecule",
            "id": "T8-07",
            "level": 3.6,
            "question": "What did Francis Crick discover?",
            "options": [
              "World Wide Web",
              "The structure of the DNA molecule",
              "gravity",
              "atomic bomb"
            ],
            "explaination": "The structure of the DNA molecule was discovered in 1953 through work at British universities in London and Cambridge. This discovery contributed to many scientific advances, particularly in medicine and fighting crime. Francis Crick (1916–2004), one of those awarded the Nobel Prize for this discovery, was British."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "1960s",
            "id": "T8-21",
            "level": 3.6,
            "question": "During which period did the Beatles become popular and social laws were liberalised?",
            "options": [
              "1950s",
              "1960s",
              "1970s",
              "1980s"
            ],
            "explaination": "The decade of the 1960s was a period of significant social change. It was known as ‘the Swinging Sixties’. There was growth in British fashion, cinema and popular music. Two well-known pop music groups at the time were The Beatles and The Rolling Stones."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Free secondary education in England and Wales",
            "id": "T9-21",
            "level": 3.6,
            "question": "What did ‘The Butler Act’ introduce in 1944?",
            "options": [
              "Free university fees in England, Wales, Scotland and Northern Ireland",
              "Free primary education in England, Wales and Scotland",
              "Free primary and secondary education in England, Wales and Scotland",
              "Free secondary education in England and Wales"
            ],
            "explaination": "Richard Austen Butler (later Lord Butler) was born in 1902. He became a Conservative MP in 1923 and held several positions before becoming responsible for education in 1941. In this role, he oversaw the introduction of the Education Act 1944 (often called ‘The Butler Act’), which introduced free secondary education in England and Wales."
          }
        ]
    },
    {
        "category": "4.1 UK Today",
        "questions":
        [
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "North west of Europe",
            "id": "T1-04",
            "level": 4.1,
            "question": "Where is the UK geographically located?",
            "options": [
              "South west of Europe",
              "South east of Europe",
              "North east of Europe",
              "North west of Europe"
            ],
            "explaination": "The UK is located in the north west of Europe."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "£25",
            "id": "T10-13",
            "level": 4.1,
            "question": "Which of the following is not a British banknote?",
            "options": [
              "£5",
              "£20",
              "£25",
              "£50"
            ],
            "explaination": "UK notes: £5, £10, £20, £50"
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Pound Sterling",
            "id": "T11-03",
            "level": 4.1,
            "question": "What is the name of the UK currency?",
            "options": [
              "Peso",
              "Euro",
              "Dollar",
              "Pound Sterling"
            ],
            "explaination": "The currency in the UK is the pound sterling (symbol £). There are 100 pence in a pound."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Women in Britain today make up about half of the workforce.",
            "id": "T12-24",
            "level": 4.1,
            "question": "Which of the following statements is true:",
            "options": [
              "Women in Britain today make up about half of the workforce.",
              "Women in Britain today make up about one quarter of the workforce."
            ],
            "explaination": "Women in Britain today make up about half of the workforce. On average, girls leave school with better qualifications than boys. More women than men study at university."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Around 10%",
            "id": "T16-11",
            "level": 4.1,
            "question": "What percentage of the UK population has a parent or grandparent born outside of the UK?",
            "options": [
              "Around 1%",
              "Around 5%",
              "Around 10%",
              "Around 15%"
            ],
            "explaination": "Post-war immigration means that nearly 10% of the population has a parent or grandparent born outside the UK. "
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "England",
            "id": "T16-19",
            "level": 4.1,
            "question": "Each of the UK countries is associated with a flower symbol, which country is associated with the rose?",
            "options": [
              "Northern Ireland",
              "Wales",
              "Scotland",
              "England"
            ],
            "explaination": "The flower associated with England is the rose.\nThe flower associated with Wales is the daffodil.\nThe flower associated with Scotland is the Thistle.\nThe flower associated with Northern Ireland is the shamrock."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "True",
            "id": "T2-13",
            "level": 4.1,
            "question": "Northern Ireland has its own banknotes, which are valid everywhere in the UK.",
            "options": [
              "True",
              "False"
            ],
            "explaination": "Northern Ireland and Scotland have their own banknotes, which are valid everywhere in the UK. However, shops and businesses do not have to accept them."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Wales",
            "id": "T3-21",
            "level": 4.1,
            "question": "Cardiff is the capital city of which country?",
            "options": [
              "England",
              "Scotland",
              "Wales",
              "Northern Ireland"
            ],
            "explaination": "United Kingdom – The capital city of the UK and England is London\nWales – The capital city of Wales is Cardiff\nNorthern Ireland – The capital city of Northern Ireland is Belfast\nScotland – The capital city of Scotland is Edinburgh"
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Daffodil",
            "id": "T4-02",
            "level": 4.1,
            "question": "Which flower is associated with Wales?",
            "options": [
              "Thistle",
              "Shamrock",
              "Daffodil",
              "Rose"
            ],
            "explaination": "The flower associated with England is the rose.\nThe flower associated with Wales is the daffodil.\nThe flower associated with Scotland is the Thistle.\nThe flower associated with Northern Ireland is the shamrock."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "True",
            "id": "T4-05",
            "level": 4.1,
            "question": "Scotland has its own banknotes, which are valid everywhere in the UK.",
            "options": [
              "True",
              "False"
            ],
            "explaination": "Northern Ireland and Scotland have their own banknotes, which are valid everywhere in the UK. However, shops and businesses do not have to accept them."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "25p",
            "id": "T5-02",
            "level": 4.1,
            "question": "Which of the following is not a valid UK coin?",
            "options": [
              "1p",
              "5p",
              "20p",
              "25p"
            ],
            "explaination": "The currency in the UK is the pound sterling (symbol £). There are 100 pence in a pound. The denominations (values) of currency are:\ncoins: 1p, 2p, 5p, 10p, 20p, 50p, £1 and £2\nnotes: £5, £10, £20, £50."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Wales",
            "id": "T6-15",
            "level": 4.1,
            "question": "Where is Swansea located?",
            "options": [
              "England",
              "Scotland",
              "Wales",
              "Northern Ireland"
            ],
            "explaination": ""
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Edinburgh",
            "id": "T7-11",
            "level": 4.1,
            "question": "What is the capital city of Scotland?",
            "options": [
              "Cardiff",
              "Edinburgh",
              "Glasgow",
              "Belfast"
            ],
            "explaination": "United Kingdom – The capital city of the UK and England is London\nWales – The capital city of Wales is Cardiff\nNorthern Ireland – The capital city of Northern Ireland is Belfast\nScotland – The capital city of Scotland is Edinburgh"
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "The Thistle",
            "id": "T8-02",
            "level": 4.1,
            "question": "Which flower is associated with Scotland?",
            "options": [
              "The Daffodil",
              "The Thistle",
              "The Shamrock",
              "The Rose"
            ],
            "explaination": "The flower associated with England is the rose.\nThe flower associated with Wales is the daffodil.\nThe flower associated with Scotland is the Thistle.\nThe flower associated with Northern Ireland is the shamrock."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "True",
            "id": "T8-08",
            "level": 4.1,
            "question": "Northern Ireland and Scotland have their own banknotes, which are valid everywhere in the UK",
            "options": [
              "True",
              "False"
            ],
            "explaination": "Northern Ireland and Scotland have their own banknotes, which are valid everywhere in the UK. However, shops and businesses do not have to accept them."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "The shamrock",
            "id": "T9-01",
            "level": 4.1,
            "question": "Which flower is associated with Northern Ireland?",
            "options": [
              "The rose",
              "The daffodil",
              "The thistle",
              "The shamrock"
            ],
            "explaination": "The flower associated with England is the rose.\nThe flower associated with Wales is the daffodil.\nThe flower associated with Scotland is the Thistle.\nThe flower associated with Northern Ireland is the shamrock."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "False",
            "id": "T9-03",
            "level": 4.1,
            "question": "£100 is the highest value note in circulation in the UK.",
            "options": [
              "True",
              "False"
            ],
            "explaination": "UK notes: £5, £10, £20, £50"
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Belfast",
            "id": "T9-09",
            "level": 4.1,
            "question": "What is the capital city of Northern Ireland?",
            "options": [
              "Dublin",
              "Cardiff",
              "Belfast",
              "Edinburgh"
            ],
            "explaination": "United Kingdom – The capital city of the UK and England is London\nWales – The capital city of Wales is Cardiff\nNorthern Ireland – The capital city of Northern Ireland is Belfast\nScotland – The capital city of Scotland is Edinburgh"
          }
        ]
    },
    {
        "category": "4.2 Religion",
        "questions":
        [
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "St Andrew",
            "id": "T1-05",
            "level": 4.2,
            "question": "Who is the patron Saint of Scotland?",
            "options": [
              "St Patrick",
              "St George",
              "St Andrew",
              "St David"
            ],
            "explaination": "1 March: St David’s Day, Wales\n17 March: St Patrick’s Day, Northern Ireland\n23 April: St George’s Day, England\n30 November: St Andrew’s Day, Scotland"
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "St George",
            "id": "T10-01",
            "level": 4.2,
            "question": "Who is the patron Saint of England?",
            "options": [
              "St Patrick",
              "St George",
              "St David",
              "St Andrew"
            ],
            "explaination": "1 March: St David’s Day, Wales\n17 March: St Patrick’s Day, Northern Ireland\n23 April: St George’s Day, England\n30 November: St Andrew’s Day, Scotland"
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "True",
            "id": "T2-03",
            "level": 4.2,
            "question": "Several Church of England bishops sit in the House of Lords.",
            "options": [
              "True",
              "False"
            ],
            "explaination": ""
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Presbyterian",
            "id": "T5-07",
            "level": 4.2,
            "question": "What sort of church is the Church of Scotland?",
            "options": [
              "Catholic",
              "Methodist",
              "Baptist",
              "Presbyterian"
            ],
            "explaination": "In Scotland, the national Church is the Church of Scotland, which is a Presbyterian Church."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "30th November",
            "id": "T11-19",
            "level": 4.2,
            "question": "When is St Andrew’s day celebrated?",
            "options": [
              "30th December",
              "1st March",
              "17th April",
              "30th November"
            ],
            "explaination": "1 March: St David’s Day, Wales\n17 March: St Patrick’s Day, Northern Ireland\n23 April: St George’s Day, England\n30 November: St Andrew’s Day, Scotland"
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "23rd April",
            "id": "T13-01",
            "level": 4.2,
            "question": "When is St George’s day?",
            "options": [
              "1st March",
              "17th March",
              "23rd April",
              "30th November"
            ],
            "explaination": "1 March: St David’s Day, Wales\n17 March: St Patrick’s Day, Northern Ireland\n23 April: St George’s Day, England\n30 November: St Andrew’s Day, Scotland"
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "The Archbishop of Canterbury",
            "id": "T13-18",
            "level": 4.2,
            "question": "Who is the spiritual leader of the Church of England?",
            "options": [
              "The Archbishop of London",
              "The Archbishop of Birmingham",
              "The Archbishop of Canterbury",
              "The Archbishop of Manchester"
            ],
            "explaination": "The monarch is the head of the Church of England. The spiritual leader of the Church of England is the Archbishop of Canterbury."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "17th March",
            "id": "T14-01",
            "level": 4.2,
            "question": "When is St Patrick’s day celebrated?",
            "options": [
              "30th November",
              "17th March",
              "1st April",
              "23rd April"
            ],
            "explaination": "1 March: St David’s Day, Wales\n17 March: St Patrick’s Day, Northern Ireland\n23 April: St George’s Day, England\n30 November: St Andrew’s Day, Scotland"
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "True",
            "id": "T2-18",
            "level": 4.2,
            "question": "St Patrick’s day is a public holiday in Northern Ireland.",
            "options": [
              "True",
              "False"
            ],
            "explaination": "Only Scotland and Northern Ireland have their patron saint’s day as an official holiday (although in Scotland not all businesses and offices will close)."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "False",
            "id": "T3-02",
            "level": 4.2,
            "question": "Wales has its own established church.",
            "options": [
              "True",
              "False"
            ],
            "explaination": "In Scotland, the national Church is the Church of Scotland, which is a Presbyterian Church. There is no established Church in Wales or Northern Ireland."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "St David",
            "id": "T3-14",
            "level": 4.2,
            "question": "Who is the patron Saint of Wales?",
            "options": [
              "St George",
              "St Patrick",
              "St David",
              "St Andrew"
            ],
            "explaination": "1 March: St David’s Day, Wales\n17 March: St Patrick’s Day, Northern Ireland\n23 April: St George’s Day, England\n30 November: St Andrew’s Day, Scotland"
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "The monarch",
            "id": "T4-12",
            "level": 4.2,
            "question": "Who is the head of the Church of England?",
            "options": [
              "The monarch",
              "The Prime Minister",
              "The Archbishop of Canterbury",
              "The bishops"
            ],
            "explaination": "The monarch is the head of the Church of England. The spiritual leader of the Church of England is the Archbishop of Canterbury. The monarch has the right to select the Archbishop and other senior church officials, but usually the choice is made by the Prime Minister and a committee appointed by the Church."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "St Patrick",
            "id": "T5-13",
            "level": 4.2,
            "question": "Who is the patron Saint of Northern Ireland?",
            "options": [
              "St Andrew",
              "St Patrick",
              "St David",
              "St George"
            ],
            "explaination": "1 March: St David’s Day, Wales\n17 March: St Patrick’s Day, Northern Ireland\n23 April: St George’s Day, England\n30 November: St Andrew’s Day, Scotland"
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "False",
            "id": "T6-05",
            "level": 4.2,
            "question": "Northern Ireland has its own established church.",
            "options": [
              "True",
              "False"
            ],
            "explaination": "There is no established Church in Wales or Northern Ireland."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "1st March",
            "id": "T8-05",
            "level": 4.2,
            "question": "When is St David’s day celebrated?",
            "options": [
              "1st March",
              "17th March",
              "23rd April",
              "30 November"
            ],
            "explaination": "1 March: St David’s Day, Wales\n17 March: St Patrick’s Day, Northern Ireland\n23 April: St George’s Day, England\n30 November: St Andrew’s Day, Scotland"
          }
        ]
    },
    {
        "category": "4.3 Customs and Traditions",
        "questions":
        [
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "A public holiday when banks and many other businesses are closed for the day",
            "id": "T1-16",
            "level": 4.3,
            "question": "What is a bank holiday?",
            "options": [
              "A public holiday for people working in banks",
              "A public holiday when banks and many other businesses are closed for the day",
              "An additional day off that every worker in the UK is entitled to",
              "A public holiday when banks are open all day"
            ],
            "explaination": "There are public holidays each year called bank holidays, when banks and many other businesses are closed for the day."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Lent",
            "id": "T1-24",
            "level": 4.3,
            "question": "What are the 40 days before Easter called?",
            "options": [
              "Hannukah",
              "Diwali",
              "Vaisakhi",
              "Lent"
            ],
            "explaination": "The 40 days before Easter are known as Lent."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "26th December",
            "id": "T10-05",
            "level": 4.3,
            "question": "When is Boxing Day celebrated?",
            "options": [
              "24th December",
              "25th December",
              "26th December",
              "27th December"
            ],
            "explaination": "Christmas Day, 25 December, celebrates the birth of Jesus Christ. Boxing Day is the day after Christmas Day and is a public holiday."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Bank Holidays",
            "id": "T10-06",
            "level": 4.3,
            "question": "What is the name of the holiday when banks and many other businesses are closed for the day?",
            "options": [
              "Business Holidays",
              "State Holidays",
              "Bank Holidays",
              "Branch Holidays"
            ],
            "explaination": "There are other public holidays each year called bank holidays, when banks and many other businesses are closed for the day."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "The Festival of Lights",
            "id": "T11-04",
            "level": 4.3,
            "question": "What other name is given to Diwali?",
            "options": [
              "Ash Wednesday",
              "The Festival of Lights",
              "Good Friday",
              "Easter Monday"
            ],
            "explaination": "Diwali normally falls in October or November and lasts for five days. It is often called the Festival of Lights. It is celebrated by Hindus and Sikhs. It celebrates the victory of good over evil and the gaining of knowledge."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Bank Holidays",
            "id": "T13-05",
            "level": 4.3,
            "question": "How are public holidays called?",
            "options": [
              "Business Holidays",
              "Bank Holidays",
              "Summer Holidays",
              "Working Holidays"
            ],
            "explaination": "There are public holidays each year called bank holidays, when banks and many other businesses are closed for the day."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "31st of December",
            "id": "T14-07",
            "level": 4.3,
            "question": "When is Hogmanay celebrated?",
            "options": [
              "25th of December",
              "31st of December",
              "1st of January",
              "2nd of January"
            ],
            "explaination": "People usually celebrate on the night of 31 December (called New Year’s Eve). In Scotland, 31 December is called Hogmanay and 2 January is also a public holiday."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Diwali",
            "id": "T17-03",
            "level": 4.3,
            "question": "Which festival is celebrated by Hindus and Sikhs and celebrated in Oct or Nov?",
            "options": [
              "Hannukah",
              "Eid al-Fitr",
              "Diwali",
              "Vaisakhi"
            ],
            "explaination": "Diwali normally falls in October or November and lasts for five days. It is often called the Festival of Lights. It is celebrated by Hindus and Sikhs. It celebrates the victory of good over evil and the gaining of knowledge."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Hindus;Sikhs",
            "id": "T2-16",
            "level": 4.3,
            "question": "Which two of the following religious communities celebrate Diwali?",
            "options": [
              "Hindus",
              "Jews",
              "Sikhs",
              "Buddhists"
            ],
            "explaination": "Diwali normally falls in October or November and lasts for five days. It is often called the Festival of Lights. It is celebrated by Hindus and Sikhs."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "The day when Jesus Christ died",
            "id": "T2-17",
            "level": 4.3,
            "question": "What is Good Friday?",
            "options": [
              "The day when Jesus Christ was born",
              "The day when Jesus Christ died",
              "The day when Jesus Christ rose from the dead",
              "The day when Jesus Christ became 10 years old"
            ],
            "explaination": "Easter takes place in March or April. It marks the death of Jesus Christ on Good Friday and his rising from the dead on Easter Sunday. Both Good Friday and the following Monday, called Easter Monday, are public holidays."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Hogmanay",
            "id": "T3-03",
            "level": 4.3,
            "question": "How is New Year’s Eve called in Scotland?",
            "options": [
              "Diwali",
              "Vaisakhi",
              "Hannukah",
              "Hogmanay"
            ],
            "explaination": "People usually celebrate on the night of 31 December (called New Year’s Eve). In Scotland, 31 December is called Hogmanay and 2 January is also a public holiday. For some Scottish people, Hogmanay is a bigger holiday than Christmas."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Eid al-Fitr",
            "id": "T3-24",
            "level": 4.3,
            "question": "Which festival celebrates the end of Ramadan, when Muslims have fasted for a month?",
            "options": [
              "Eid ul Adha",
              "Eid al-Fitr",
              "Hannukah",
              "Vaisakhi"
            ],
            "explaination": "Eid al-Fitr celebrates the end of Ramadan, when Muslims have fasted for a month.\nEid ul Adha remembers that the prophet Ibrahim was willing to sacrifice his son when God ordered him to. It reminds Muslims of their own commitment to God.\nHannukah is in November or December and is celebrated for eight days. It is to remember the Jews’ struggle for religious freedom.\nVaisakhi (also spelled Baisakhi) is a Sikh festival which celebrates the founding of the Sikh community known as the Khalsa."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "25th of December",
            "id": "T4-15",
            "level": 4.3,
            "question": "When is Christmas Day?",
            "options": [
              "24th of December",
              "25th of December",
              "26th of December",
              "27th of December"
            ],
            "explaination": "Christmas Day, 25 December, celebrates the birth of Jesus Christ."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "March or April",
            "id": "T5-01",
            "level": 4.3,
            "question": "When does Easter take place?",
            "options": [
              "January or February",
              "March or April",
              "May or June",
              "November or December"
            ],
            "explaination": "Easter takes place in March or April. It marks the death of Jesus Christ on Good Friday and his rising from the dead on Easter Sunday. Both Good Friday and the following Monday, called Easter Monday, are public holidays."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "April Fool’s Day",
            "id": "T5-09",
            "level": 4.3,
            "question": "When do the television and newspapers have stories that are jokes until midday?",
            "options": [
              "Valentine’s Day",
              "April Fool’s Day",
              "Halloween",
              "Boxing Day"
            ],
            "explaination": "On April Fool’s Day, the 1st of April the television and newspapers often have stories that are April Fool jokes."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Christmas Day",
            "id": "T6-13",
            "level": 4.3,
            "question": "On what day is the birth of Jesus Christ celebrated?",
            "options": [
              "New Year",
              "Easter",
              "Christmas Day",
              "Boxing Day"
            ],
            "explaination": "Christmas Day, 25 December, celebrates the birth of Jesus Christ."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "31st of October",
            "id": "T7-02",
            "level": 4.3,
            "question": "When is Halloween celebrated?",
            "options": [
              "1st of April",
              "30th of October",
              "31st of October",
              "11th of November"
            ],
            "explaination": "Halloween, 31 October, is an ancient festival and has roots in the pagan festival to mark the beginning of winter."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "The 40 days before Easter",
            "id": "T7-23",
            "level": 4.3,
            "question": "What is known as Lent?",
            "options": [
              "The 40 days after Easter",
              "The 40 days before Easter",
              "The 40 days before Christmas",
              "The 40 days after Christmas"
            ],
            "explaination": "The 40 days before Easter are known as Lent. It is a time when Christians take time to reflect and prepare for Easter."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Good Friday",
            "id": "T8-12",
            "level": 4.3,
            "question": "What day relates to the death of Jesus Christ?",
            "options": [
              "Good Friday",
              "Ash Wednesday",
              "Easter Sunday",
              "Easter Monday"
            ],
            "explaination": "Easter takes place in March or April. It marks the death of Jesus Christ on Good Friday and his rising from the dead on Easter Sunday."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "New Year's Eve in Scotland",
            "id": "T9-08",
            "level": 4.3,
            "question": "What does Hogmanay refer to?",
            "options": [
              "New Year's Eve in Wales",
              "New Year's Eve in Scotland",
              "Christmas Day in Wales",
              "Christmas Day in Scotland"
            ],
            "explaination": "People usually celebrate on the night of 31 December (called New Year’s Eve). In Scotland, 31 December is called Hogmanay and 2 January is also a public holiday."
          }
        ]
    },
    {
        "category": "4.4 Sport",
        "questions":
        [
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Bobby Moore",
            "id": "T1-11",
            "level": 4.4,
            "question": "Who was the captain of the English football team that won the World Cup in 1966?",
            "options": [
              "Sir Ian Botham",
              "Bobby Moore",
              "Sir Jackie Stewart",
              "Sir Roger Bannister"
            ],
            "explaination": "Bobby Moore captained the English football team that won the World Cup in 1966."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Ayr",
            "id": "T10-14",
            "level": 4.4,
            "question": "Where does the Scottish Grand National take place?",
            "options": [
              "Ayr",
              "Edinburgh",
              "Aberdeen",
              "Glasgow"
            ],
            "explaination": "Famous horse-racing events include: Royal Ascot, a five-day race meeting in Berkshire attended by members of the Royal Family; the Grand National at Aintree near Liverpool; and the Scottish Grand National at Ayr."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "The University of Oxford;The University of Cambridge",
            "id": "T10-23",
            "level": 4.4,
            "question": "Which two universities participate in an annual rowing race that takes place on the River Thames?",
            "options": [
              "The University of Oxford",
              "The University of Manchester",
              "The University of Cambridge",
              "The University of Warwick"
            ],
            "explaination": "Rowing is also popular, both as a leisure activity and as a competitive sport. There is a popular yearly race on the Thames between Oxford and Cambridge Universities."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Wimbledon",
            "id": "T12-11",
            "level": 4.4,
            "question": "What is the most famous tennis tournament played in the UK?",
            "options": [
              "Open Championship",
              "Royal Ascot",
              "Wimbledon",
              "Six Nations Championship"
            ],
            "explaination": "Modern tennis evolved in England in the late 19th century. The most famous tournament hosted in Britain is The Wimbledon Championships, which takes place each year at the All England Lawn Tennis and Croquet Club. It is the oldest tennis tournament in the world and the only ‘Grand Slam’ event played on grass."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Newmarket, Suffolk",
            "id": "T13-22",
            "level": 4.4,
            "question": "Where is the National Horseracing Museum located?",
            "options": [
              "St Andrews, Scotland",
              "Edinburgh, Scotland",
              "Newmarket, Suffolk",
              "Aintree near Liverpool"
            ],
            "explaination": "There is a National Horseracing Museum in Newmarket, Suffolk."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "The Six Nations Championship",
            "id": "T14-09",
            "level": 4.4,
            "question": "Which of the following is a rugby competition?",
            "options": [
              "The Open Championship",
              "The Six Nations Championship",
              "The Grand National",
              "Royal Ascot"
            ],
            "explaination": "The most famous rugby union competition is the Six Nations Championship between England, Ireland, Scotland, Wales, France and Italy. The Super League is the most well-known rugby league (club) competition."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "3",
            "id": "T14-19",
            "level": 4.4,
            "question": "How many times has the UK hosted the Olympic games?",
            "options": [
              "2",
              "3",
              "4",
              "5"
            ],
            "explaination": "The UK has hosted the Olympic Games on three occasions: 1908, 1948 and 2012."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Ellie Simmonds",
            "id": "T16-18",
            "level": 4.4,
            "question": "Which Paralympic athlete has won gold medals for swimming at the 2008, 2012 and 2016 Paralympic Games?",
            "options": [
              "David Weir",
              "Baroness Tanni-Grey Thompson",
              "Ellie Simmonds",
              "Mo Farah"
            ],
            "explaination": "Ellie Simmonds (1994–) is a Paralympian who won gold medals for swimming at the 2008 and 2012 Paralympic Games and holds a number of world records."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Motor sports",
            "id": "T17-07",
            "level": 4.4,
            "question": "Damon Hill, Lewis Hamilton and Jensen Button are known for which sports",
            "options": [
              "Motor sports",
              "Skiing",
              "Water sports",
              "Horse racing"
            ],
            "explaination": "A Formula 1 Grand Prix event is held in the UK each year and a number of British Grand Prix drivers have won the Formula 1 World Championship. Recent British winners include Damon Hill, Lewis Hamilton and Jensen Button."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Golf",
            "id": "T2-21",
            "level": 4.4,
            "question": "Which sport can be traced back to the 15th century in Scotland?",
            "options": [
              "Rugby",
              "Golf",
              "Tennis",
              "Football"
            ],
            "explaination": "The modern game of golf can be traced back to 15th century Scotland."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Sir Roger Bannister",
            "id": "T3-23",
            "level": 4.4,
            "question": "Who was the first man in the world to run 1 mile in under 4 minutes?",
            "options": [
              "Mo Farah",
              "David Weir",
              "Sir Chris Hoy",
              "Sir Roger Bannister"
            ],
            "explaination": "Sir Roger Bannister (1929–) was the first man in the world to run a mile in under four minutes, in 1954."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Horse Racing",
            "id": "T4-13",
            "level": 4.4,
            "question": "What sort of event is the Grand National?",
            "options": [
              "Motor-car",
              "Tennis",
              "Golf",
              "Horse Racing"
            ],
            "explaination": "Famous horse-racing events include: Royal Ascot, a five-day race meeting in Berkshire attended by members of the Royal Family; the Grand National at Aintree near Liverpool; and the Scottish Grand National at Ayr."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Scotland",
            "id": "T5-08",
            "level": 4.4,
            "question": "Where does golf come from?",
            "options": [
              "Australia",
              "Wales",
              "Northern Ireland",
              "Scotland"
            ],
            "explaination": "The modern game of golf can be traced back to 15th century Scotland."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Baroness Tanni Grey-Thompson;Ellie Simmonds",
            "id": "T6-10",
            "level": 4.4,
            "question": "Which two of the following are famous British Paralympians?",
            "options": [
              "Baroness Tanni Grey-Thompson",
              "Jayne Torvill",
              "Ellie Simmonds",
              "Dame Kelly Holmes"
            ],
            "explaination": "Ellie Simmonds (1994–) is a Paralympian who won gold medals for swimming at the 2008 and 2012 Paralympic Games and holds a number of world records. \nBaroness Tanni-Grey Thompson (1969–) is an athlete who uses a wheelchair and won 16 Paralympic medals, including 11 gold medals, in races over five Paralympic Games.\nDavid Weir (1979–) is a Paralympian who uses a wheelchair and has won six gold medals over two Paralympic Games."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "The Ashes",
            "id": "T7-04",
            "level": 4.4,
            "question": "What is the name of the most famous cricket competition played between England and Australia?",
            "options": [
              "The Grand National",
              "The Australian Open",
              "The Six Nations Championship",
              "The Ashes"
            ],
            "explaination": "The most famous competition is the Ashes, which is a series of Test matches played between England and Australia."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Royal Ascot",
            "id": "T7-21",
            "level": 4.4,
            "question": "Which of the following is a major horse-racing event in England?",
            "options": [
              "Royal Ascot",
              "The Open Championship",
              "The Wimbledon Championships",
              "The Six Nations Championship"
            ],
            "explaination": "Famous horse-racing events include: Royal Ascot, a five-day race meeting in Berkshire attended by members of the Royal Family; the Grand National at Aintree near Liverpool; and the Scottish Grand National at Ayr."
          },
          {
              "id": "T12-20",
              "question": "Which of the following major sports event took place in the UK in 2012?",
              "answer": "The Olympic games",
              "options":["The Rugby World Cup", "The Olympic games", "The Football World Cup", "The Eurocup Basketball"],
              "explaination": "The UK has hosted the Olympic Games on three occasions: 1908, 1948 and 2012.",
              "star": true,
              "level": 4.4,
          }
        ]
    },
    {
        "category": "4.5 Arts and Culture",
        "questions": 
        [
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "A war memorial",
            "id": "T1-08",
            "level": 4.5,
            "question": "What is the Cenotaph?",
            "options": [
              "A Christian church",
              "A flower",
              "A place",
              "A war memorial"
            ],
            "explaination": "The Cenotaph is a war memorial and it is the site of the annual Remembrance Day service attended by the Queen, politicians and foreign ambassadors."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "William Wordsworth",
            "id": "T1-22",
            "level": 4.5,
            "question": "Who wrote ‘The Daffodils’?",
            "options": [
              "Lord Byron",
              "William Wordsworth",
              "Robert Browning",
              "William Blake"
            ],
            "explaination": "The British poet William Wordsworth wrote ‘The Daffodils’."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Edinburgh",
            "id": "T10-09",
            "level": 4.5,
            "question": "Where does “the Fringe” festival take place?",
            "options": [
              "Cardiff",
              "London",
              "Edinburgh",
              "Ayr"
            ],
            "explaination": "The Edinburgh Festival takes place in Edinburgh, Scotland, every summer. It is a series of different arts and cultural festivals, with the biggest and most well-known being the Edinburgh Festival Fringe (‘the Fringe’). The Fringe is a showcase of mainly theatre and comedy performances. It often shows experimental work."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "He was a musician",
            "id": "T10-12",
            "level": 4.5,
            "question": "What was Edward Elgar famous for?",
            "options": [
              "He was a tennis player",
              "He was a musician",
              "He was an actor",
              "He was a director"
            ],
            "explaination": "Sir Edward Elgar (1857–1934) was born in Worcester, England. His best-known work is probably the Pomp and Circumstance Marches. March No 1 (Land of Hope and Glory) is usually played at the Last Night of the Proms at the Royal Albert Hall."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "An eight-week summer season of daily orchestral classical music concerts",
            "id": "T10-19",
            "level": 4.5,
            "question": "What is “the Proms”?",
            "options": [
              "Light-hearted plays with music and comedy",
              "An annual cultural festival which includes music, dance, art and original performances largely in Welsh",
              "An eight-week summer season of daily orchestral classical music concerts",
              "An annual event that gives awards in a range of categories, such as best British group and best British solo artist"
            ],
            "explaination": "The Proms is an eight-week summer season of orchestral classical music that takes place in various venues, including the Royal Albert Hall in London. It has been organised by the British Broadcasting Corporation (BBC) since 1927. The Last Night of the Proms is the most well-known concert and (along with others in the series) is broadcast on television."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "London’s West End",
            "id": "T11-02",
            "level": 4.5,
            "question": "Where is Theatreland?",
            "options": [
              "London’s East End",
              "London’s South End",
              "London’s West End",
              "Docklands"
            ],
            "explaination": "There are theatres in most towns and cities throughout the UK, ranging from the large to the small. They are an important part of local communities and often show both professional and amateur productions. London’s West End, also known as ‘Theatreland’, is particularly well known."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Cenotaph",
            "id": "T11-12",
            "level": 4.5,
            "question": "What is the name of the War Memorial located in Whitehall?",
            "options": [
              "The White Tower",
              "Tower of London",
              "Cenotaph",
              "Stonehenge"
            ],
            "explaination": "In the 20th century, Sir Edwin Lutyens had an influence throughout the British Empire. He designed New Delhi to be the seat of government in India. After the First World War, he was responsible for many war memorials throughout the world, including the Cenotaph in Whitehall. The Cenotaph is the site of the annual Remembrance Day service attended by the Queen, politicians and foreign ambassadors."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Daffodil",
            "id": "T11-18",
            "level": 4.5,
            "question": "What flower did William Wordsworth write about?",
            "options": [
              "Daffodil",
              "Thistle",
              "Rose",
              "Shamrock"
            ],
            "explaination": "‘I wander’d lonely as a cloud,\nThat floats on high o’er vales and hills,\nWhen all at once I saw a crowd,\nA host of golden daffodils’\n(William Wordsworth, 1770–1850 – The Daffodils)"
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "London",
            "id": "T12-07",
            "level": 4.5,
            "question": "Where is the Tate Art Gallery located?",
            "options": [
              "London",
              "Cardiff",
              "Glasgow",
              "Belfast"
            ],
            "explaination": "Works by British and international artists are displayed in galleries across the UK. Some of the most well-known galleries are The National Gallery, Tate Britain and Tate Modern in London, the National Museum in Cardiff, and the National Gallery of Scotland in Edinburgh."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "William Wordsworth",
            "id": "T13-15",
            "level": 4.5,
            "question": "Which of the following poets was inspired by nature?",
            "options": [
              "Wilfred Owen",
              "William Wordsworth",
              "William Caxton",
              "Dylan Thomas"
            ],
            "explaination": "William Wordsworth, were inspired by nature. Sir Walter Scott wrote poems inspired by Scotland and the traditional stories and songs from the area on the borders of Scotland and England."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Clarice Cliff",
            "id": "T13-24",
            "level": 4.5,
            "question": "Who was a famous Art Deco ceramic designer?",
            "options": [
              "Thomas Chippendale",
              "Clarice Cliff",
              "Mary Quant",
              "Sir Terence Conran"
            ],
            "explaination": "Britain has produced many great designers, from Thomas Chippendale (who designed furniture in the 18th century) to Clarice Cliff (who designed Art Deco ceramics) to Sir Terence Conran (a 20th-century interior designer). Leading fashion designers of recent years include Mary Quant, Alexander McQueen and Vivienne Westwood."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Harry Potter",
            "id": "T15-04",
            "level": 4.5,
            "question": "Which film produced in the UK was one of the most commercially successful films of all time and one of the highest-grossing film franchises?",
            "options": [
              "Four Weddings and a Funeral",
              "Harry Potter",
              "The Lord of the Rings",
              "Wallace and Gromit"
            ],
            "explaination": "Some of the most commercially successful films of all time, including the two highest- grossing film franchises (Harry Potter and James Bond), have been produced in the UK."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "James Bond",
            "id": "T16-05",
            "level": 4.5,
            "question": "What is one of the highest-grossing film franchises produced in the UK?",
            "options": [
              "The Lord of the Rings",
              "Star Wars",
              "James Bond",
              "Spiderman"
            ],
            "explaination": "Many of the films now produced in the UK are made by foreign companies, using British expertise. Some of the most commercially successful films of all time, including the two highest- grossing film franchises (Harry Potter and James Bond), have been produced in the UK."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "The White Tower",
            "id": "T16-15",
            "level": 4.5,
            "question": "Which historical monument did William the Conqueror build?",
            "options": [
              "The Cenotaph",
              "St Paul’s Cathedral",
              "Hadrian's Wall",
              "The White Tower"
            ],
            "explaination": "The White Tower in the Tower of London is an example of a Norman castle keep, built on the orders of William the Conqueror."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "The Pomp and Circumstance Marches;Land of Hope and Glory",
            "id": "T17-18",
            "level": 4.5,
            "question": "Which two of below was Edward Elgar's best-known work?",
            "options": [
              "The Pomp and Circumstance Marches",
              "Auld Lang Syne",
              "Façade",
              "Land of Hope and Glory"
            ],
            "explaination": "Sir Edward Elgar (1857–1934) was born in Worcester, England. His best-known work is probably the Pomp and Circumstance Marches. March No 1 (Land of Hope and Glory) is usually played at the Last Night of the Proms at the Royal Albert Hall."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "David Hockney",
            "id": "T2-08",
            "level": 4.5,
            "question": "Who was an important contributor to the ‘pop art’ movement of the 1960’s?",
            "options": [
              "Henry Moore",
              "John Petts",
              "Lucian Freud",
              "David Hockney"
            ],
            "explaination": "David Hockney was an important contributor to the ‘pop art’ movement of the 1960s and continues to be influential today."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Sir Arthur Conan Doyle",
            "id": "T3-12",
            "level": 4.5,
            "question": "Who wrote Sherlock Holmes?",
            "options": [
              "Sir Kingsley Amis",
              "Sir Arthur Conan Doyle",
              "Graham Greene",
              "Evelyn Waugh"
            ],
            "explaination": "Sir Arthur Conan Doyle (1859–1930) was a Scottish doctor and writer. He was best known for his stories about Sherlock Holmes, who was one of the first fictional detectives."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Theatreland",
            "id": "T3-16",
            "level": 4.5,
            "question": "What is the name of the area in London where famous theatres are located?",
            "options": [
              "Soho",
              "Hyde Park",
              "Westminster",
              "Theatreland"
            ],
            "explaination": "There are theatres in most towns and cities throughout the UK, ranging from the large to the small. London’s West End, also known as ‘Theatreland’, is particularly well known."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "The Lord of the Rings",
            "id": "T5-23",
            "level": 4.5,
            "question": "Which novel written by JRR Tolkien was voted the country’s best-loved novel in 2003?",
            "options": [
              "James Bond",
              "The Lord of the Rings",
              "Oliver Twist",
              "Pride and Prejudice"
            ],
            "explaination": "In 2003, The Lord of the Rings by JRR Tolkien was voted the country’s best-loved novel."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "William the Conqueror",
            "id": "T6-03",
            "level": 4.5,
            "question": "Who built the Tower of London?",
            "options": [
              "Oliver Cromwell",
              "William the Conqueror",
              "Queen Elizabeth I",
              "Henry VIII"
            ],
            "explaination": "The Tower of London was first built by William the Conqueror after he became king in 1066."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Sir Edwin Lutyens",
            "id": "T8-19",
            "level": 4.5,
            "question": "Who designed the Cenotaph?",
            "options": [
              "Sir Christopher Wren",
              "Sir Edwin Lutyens",
              "Isambard Kingdom Brunel",
              "Robert Adam"
            ],
            "explaination": "In the 20th century, Sir Edwin Lutyens had an influence throughout the British Empire. He designed New Delhi to be the seat of government in India. After the First World War, he was responsible for many war memorials throughout the world, including the Cenotaph in Whitehall."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "Literature",
            "id": "T8-22",
            "level": 4.5,
            "question": "The Man Booker Prize is awarded in which of the following categories?",
            "options": [
              "Music",
              "Art",
              "Films",
              "Literature"
            ],
            "explaination": "The Man Booker Prize for Fiction is awarded annually for the best fiction novel written by an author from the Commonwealth, Ireland or Zimbabwe."
          },
          {
            "star": true,
            "answer": "A contemporary art award",
            "id": "T8-24",
            "level": 4.5,
            "question": "What is the Turner Prize?",
            "options": [
              "A literature award",
              "A contemporary art award",
              "A music award",
              "A film award"
            ],
            "explaination": "The Turner Prize was established in 1984 and celebrates contemporary art. It was named after Joseph Turner. Four works are shortlisted every year and shown at Tate Britain before the winner is announced. The Turner Prize is recognised as one of the most prestigious visual art awards in Europe."
          }
        ]
    },
    {
        "category": "4.6 Leisure",
        "questions":
        [
           {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "18",
              "id": "T11-24",
              "level": 4.6,
              "question": "How old do you have to be to buy alcohol in the UK?",
              "options": [
                 "16",
                 "17",
                 "18",
                 "20"
              ],
              "explaination": "It is a criminal offence to sell alcohol to anyone who is under 18 or to buy alcohol for people who are under the age of 18. (There is one exception: people aged 16 or over can drink alcohol with a meal in a hotel or restaurant."
           },
           {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "No",
              "id": "T12-02",
              "level": 4.6,
              "question": "Is the BBC controlled by the government?",
              "options": [
                 "Yes",
                 "No"
              ],
              "explaination": "BBC is a British public service broadcaster providing television and radio programmes. The BBC is the largest broadcaster in the world. It is the only wholly state-funded media organisation that is independent of government."
           },
           {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "Charlie Chaplin",
              "id": "T13-12",
              "level": 4.6,
              "question": "Who became famous for his tramp character in silent movies?",
              "options": [
                 "Sir Lawrence Olivier",
                 "David Niven",
                 "Sir Rex Harrison",
                 "Charlie Chaplin"
              ],
              "explaination": "Sir Charles (Charlie) Chaplin became famous in silent movies for his tramp character and was one of many British actors to make a career in Hollywood."
           },
           {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "Most shops in the UK open seven days a week.",
              "id": "T13-20",
              "level": 4.6,
              "question": "Which of the following statements is correct?",
              "options": [
                 "Most shops in the UK open seven days a week.",
                 "All shops in the UK close on Sundays and bank holidays."
              ],
              "explaination": "Most shops in the UK are open seven days a week, although trading hours on Sundays and public holidays are generally reduced. "
           },
           {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "Crathes Castle",
              "id": "T13-23",
              "level": 4.6,
              "question": "Which of the following castles is located in Scotland?",
              "options": [
                 "Bodiam Castle",
                 "Crathes Castle",
                 "Maiden Castle",
                 "Powis Castle"
              ],
              "explaination": "There are famous gardens to visit throughout the UK, including Kew Gardens, Sissinghurst and Hidcote in England, Crathes Castle and Inveraray Castle in Scotland, Bodnant Garden in Wales, and Mount Stewart in Northern Ireland."
           },
           {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "Emily Watson",
              "id": "T14-04",
              "level": 4.6,
              "question": "Which of the following actresses has not won an Oscar?",
              "options": [
                 "Colin Firth",
                 "Dame Judi Dench",
                 "Emily Watson",
                 "Kate Winslet"
              ],
              "explaination": "Recent British actors to have won Oscars include Colin Firth, Sir Anthony Hopkins, Dame Judi Dench, Kate Winslet and Tilda Swinton."
           },
           {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "18",
              "id": "T14-15",
              "level": 4.6,
              "question": "How old do you have to be to go into betting shops or gambling clubs?",
              "options": [
                 "17",
                 "18",
                 "16",
                 "21"
              ],
              "explaination": "In the UK, people often enjoy a gamble on sports or other events. There are also casinos in many places. You have to be 18 to go into betting shops or gambling clubs."
           },
           {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "Ulster Fry",
              "id": "T14-17",
              "level": 4.6,
              "question": "What is the traditional food of Northern Ireland?",
              "options": [
                 "Haggis",
                 "Ulster Fry",
                 "Roast beef",
                 "Welsh cakes"
              ],
              "explaination": "There are a variety of foods that are traditionally associated with different parts of the UK:\nEngland: Roast beef. Fish and chips are also popular.\nWales: Welsh cakes\nScotland: Haggis\nNorthern Ireland: Ulster fry"
           },
           {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "An animated film",
              "id": "T15-23",
              "level": 4.6,
              "question": "What kind of genre was the film Wallace and Gromit created by Nick Park?",
              "options": [
                 "An action film",
                 "An animated film",
                 "A silent movie",
                 "A soap opera"
              ],
              "explaination": "The work of Nick Park, who has won four Oscars for his animated films, including three for films featuring Wallace and Gromit."
           },
           {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "Wallace and Gromit",
              "id": "T16-09",
              "level": 4.6,
              "question": "Nick Park has won four Oscars for his animated films, including three for films featuring:",
              "options": [
                 "Touching the Void",
                 "Lawrence of Arabia",
                 "Four Weddings and a Funeral",
                 "Wallace and Gromit"
              ],
              "explaination": "Britain continues to be particularly strong in special effects and animation. One example is the work of Nick Park, who has won four Oscars for his animated films, including three for films featuring Wallace and Gromit."
           },
           {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "Animated movies",
              "id": "T16-24",
              "level": 4.6,
              "question": "What kind of movies did Academy Award winner Nick Park specialise in?",
              "options": [
                 "Action movies",
                 "Animated movies",
                 "Silent movies",
                 "Horror movies"
              ],
              "explaination": "The work of Nick Park, who has won four Oscars for his animated films, including three for films featuring Wallace and Gromit."
           },
           {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "Pool and Darts",
              "id": "T17-27",
              "level": 4.6,
              "question": "What kind of games people would play at pubs?",
              "options": [
                 "Dominoes",
                 "Bar billiards",
                 "Quarters",
                 "Pool and Darts"
              ],
              "explaination": "Most communities will have a ‘local’ pub that is a natural focal point for social activities. Pub quizzes are popular. Pool and darts are traditional pub games."
           },
           {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "That your dog wears a collar showing the name and address of the owner",
              "id": "T2-04",
              "level": 4.6,
              "question": "When walking your dog in a public place, you must ensure:",
              "options": [
                 "That your dog does not play with other dogs",
                 "That your dog does not bark",
                 "That your dog wears a collar showing the name and address of the owner",
                 "That your dog wears a high visibility jacket"
              ],
              "explaination": "All dogs in public places must wear a collar showing the name and address of the owner."
           },
           {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "A tramp",
              "id": "T4-20",
              "level": 4.6,
              "question": "What type of character was played by Charlie Chaplin?",
              "options": [
                 "A scientific genius",
                 "A bandit",
                 "A tramp",
                 "A superhero"
              ],
              "explaination": "Sir Charles (Charlie) Chaplin became famous in silent movies for his tramp character and was one of many British actors to make a career in Hollywood."
           },
           {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "Scotland",
              "id": "T6-19",
              "level": 4.6,
              "question": "Haggis is a traditional food from which area?",
              "options": [
                 "England",
                 "Scotland",
                 "Wales",
                 "Northern Ireland"
              ],
              "explaination": "There are a variety of foods that are traditionally associated with different parts of the UK:\nEngland: Roast beef. Fish and chips are also popular.\nWales: Welsh cakes\nScotland: Haggis\nNorthern Ireland: Ulster fry"
           },
           {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "The owner's address;The owner's name",
              "id": "T8-11",
              "level": 4.6,
              "question": "If you are a dog owner, which two things should your dog’s collar have when you go out for a walk?",
              "options": [
                 "The owner's name",
                 "The owner's address",
                 "The dog's name",
                 "The dog's breed"
              ],
              "explaination": "All dogs in public places must wear a collar showing the name and address of the owner. The owner is responsible for keeping the dog under control and for cleaning up after the animal in a public place."
           }
        ]
    },
    {
        "category": "4.7 Places of interest",
        "questions": [
            {
               "star": true,
               "answer": "The Houses of the Parliament",
               "id": "T1-02",
               "level": 4.7,
               "question": "Where is Big Ben located?",
               "options": [
                  "Buckingham Palace",
                  "The Tower of London",
                  "Trafalgar Square",
                  "The Houses of the Parliament"
               ],
               "explaination": "Big Ben is the nickname for the great bell of the clock at the Houses of Parliament in London."
            },
            {
               "star": true,
               "answer": "Scotland",
               "id": "T10-02",
               "level": 4.7,
               "question": "Where is Loch Lomond and the Trossachs National Park located?",
               "options": [
                  "England",
                  "Wales",
                  "Northern Ireland",
                  "Scotland"
               ],
               "explaination": "Loch Lomond and the Trossachs National Park covers 720 square miles (1,865 square kilometres) in the west of Scotland. Loch Lomond is the largest expanse of fresh water in mainland Britain and probably the best- known part of the park."
            },
            {
               "star": true,
               "answer": "The Lake District",
               "id": "T13-02",
               "level": 4.7,
               "question": "Which is the largest National Park in England?",
               "options": [
                  "Loch Lomond and the Trossachs National Park",
                  "Snowdonia",
                  "The Lake District",
                  "The Giant’s Causeway"
               ],
               "explaination": "The Lake District is England’s largest national park. It covers 885 square miles (2,292 square kilometres)."
            },
            {
               "star": true,
               "answer": "The Tower of London",
               "id": "T13-09",
               "level": 4.7,
               "question": "Where do Beefeaters serve as tour guides?",
               "options": [
                  "The Big Ben",
                  "The Tower of London",
                  "The Houses of the Parliament",
                  "Edinburgh Castle"
               ],
               "explaination": "The Tower of London was first built by William the Conqueror after he became king in 1066. Tours are given by the Yeoman Warders, also known as Beefeaters, who tell visitors about the building’s history."
            },
            {
               "star": true,
               "answer": "Northern Ireland",
               "id": "T16-02",
               "level": 4.7,
               "question": "Where is the Giant’s Causeway located?",
               "options": [
                  "England",
                  "Scotland",
                  "Wales",
                  "Northern Ireland"
               ],
               "explaination": "Located on the north-east coast of Northern Ireland, the Giant’s Causeway is a land formation of columns made from volcanic lava. It was formed about 50 million years ago. There are many legends about the Causeway and how it was formed."
            },
            {
               "star": true,
               "answer": "Eden Project",
               "id": "T17-42",
               "level": 4.7,
               "question": "What is landmark which located in Cornwall, in the south west of England?",
               "options": [
                  "The Giant’s Causeway",
                  "Eden Project",
                  "Snowdonia",
                  "Loch Lomond and the Trossachs National Park"
               ],
               "explaination": "The Eden Project is located in Cornwall, in the south west of England. Its biomes, which are like giant greenhouses, house plants from all over the world."
            },
            {
               "star": true,
               "answer": "The Tower of London",
               "id": "T17-44",
               "level": 4.7,
               "question": "Which historical monument did William the Conqueror build?",
               "options": [
                  "The Cenotaph",
                  "The Tower of London",
                  "Hadrian's Wall",
                  "St Paul’s Cathedral"
               ],
               "explaination": "The White Tower in the Tower of London is an example of a Norman castle keep, built on the orders of William the Conqueror."
            },
            {
               "star": true,
               "answer": "the Tower of London",
               "id": "T2-20",
               "level": 4.7,
               "question": "Where are the Crown Jewels kept?",
               "options": [
                  "the Tower of London",
                  "Buckingham Palace",
                  "Windsor Castle",
                  "the House of Commons"
               ],
               "explaination": "The Tower of London was first built by William the Conqueror after he became king in 1066. Tours are given by the Yeoman Warders, also known as Beefeaters, who tell visitors about the building’s history. People can also see the Crown Jewels there."
            },
            {
               "star": true,
               "answer": "Beefeaters",
               "id": "T3-09",
               "level": 4.7,
               "question": "What is the name of the tour guides that tell visitors stories about the Tower of London’s history?",
               "options": [
                  "Suffragettes",
                  "Chartists",
                  "Knights",
                  "Beefeaters"
               ],
               "explaination": "The Tower of London was first built by William the Conqueror after he became king in 1066. Tours are given by the Yeoman Warders, also known as Beefeaters, who tell visitors about the building’s history."
            },
            {
               "star": true,
               "answer": "Wales",
               "id": "T3-11",
               "level": 4.7,
               "question": "Where is Snowdonia located?",
               "options": [
                  "England",
                  "Scotland",
                  "Wales",
                  "Northern Ireland"
               ],
               "explaination": "Snowdonia is a national park in North Wales."
            },
            {
               "star": true,
               "answer": "True",
               "id": "T3-15",
               "level": 4.7,
               "question": "Lake District is the largest national park of England.",
               "options": [
                  "True",
                  "False"
               ],
               "explaination": "The Lake District is England’s largest national park. It covers 885 square miles (2,292 square kilometres)."
            },
            {
               "star": true,
               "answer": "The National Trust",
               "id": "T4-06",
               "level": 4.7,
               "question": "What charity works to preserve important buildings, coastline and countryside in the UK?",
               "options": [
                  "Friends of the Earth",
                  "Crisis and Shelter",
                  "The National Trust",
                  "County Courts"
               ],
               "explaination": "Many parts of the countryside and places of interest are kept open by the National Trust in England, Wales and Northern Ireland and the National Trust for Scotland. Both are charities that work to preserve important buildings, coastline and countryside in the UK."
            },
            {
               "star": true,
               "answer": "Cornwall",
               "id": "T5-03",
               "level": 4.7,
               "question": "Where is the Eden Project located?",
               "options": [
                  "Devon",
                  "Dorset",
                  "Cornwall",
                  "Somerset"
               ],
               "explaination": "The Eden Project is located in Cornwall, in the south west of England. Its biomes, which are like giant greenhouses, house plants from all over the world."
            },
            {
               "star": true,
               "answer": "Areas of protected countryside",
               "id": "T6-04",
               "level": 4.7,
               "question": "There are 15 national parks in England, Wales and Scotland. What are national parks?",
               "options": [
                  "Giant greenhouses",
                  "Areas of protected countryside",
                  "Land formations of columns made from volcanic lava",
                  "Medieval buildings"
               ],
               "explaination": "There are 15 national parks in England, Wales and Scotland. They are areas of protected countryside that everyone can visit, and where people live, work and look after the landscape."
            },
            {
               "star": true,
               "answer": "Lake District",
               "id": "T7-17",
               "level": 4.7,
               "question": "What UK landmark was voted as Britain’s favourite view in 2007?",
               "options": [
                  "Lake District",
                  "The Big Ben",
                  "The London Eye",
                  "Snowdonia"
               ],
               "explaination": "The Lake District is England’s largest national park. It covers 885 square miles (2,292 square kilometres). It is famous for its lakes and mountains and is very popular with climbers, walkers and sailors. The biggest stretch of water is Windermere. In 2007, television viewers voted Wastwater as Britain’s favourite view."
            },
            {
               "star": true,
               "answer": "15",
               "id": "T8-09",
               "level": 4.7,
               "question": "How many national parks are there in England, Wales and Scotland?",
               "options": [
                  "15",
                  "18",
                  "20",
                  "40"
               ],
               "explaination": "There are 15 national parks in England, Wales and Scotland. They are areas of protected countryside that everyone can visit, and where people live, work and look after the landscape."
            },
            {
               "star": true,
               "answer": "England",
               "id": "T9-04",
               "level": 4.7,
               "question": "Where is the Lake District National Park located?",
               "options": [
                  "England",
                  "Scotland",
                  "Wales",
                  "Northern Ireland"
               ],
               "explaination": "The Lake District is England’s largest national park. It covers 885 square miles (2,292 square kilometres). It is famous for its lakes and mountains and is very popular with climbers, walkers and sailors."
            }
         ]
    },
    {
        "category": "5.2 The British constitution",
        "questions":
        [
           {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "The Speaker",
              "id": "T1-10",
              "level": 5.2,
              "question": "Who chairs the debates at the House of Commons?",
              "options": [
                 "The Speaker",
                 "A bishop",
                 "The archbishop of Canterbury",
                 "The Prime Minister"
              ],
              "explaination": "Debates in the House of Commons are chaired by the Speaker."
           },
           {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "No",
              "id": "T10-24",
              "level": 5.2,
              "question": "Does Britain have a written constitution?",
              "options": [
                 "Yes",
                 "No"
              ],
              "explaination": "The British constitution is not written down in any single document, and therefore it is described as ‘unwritten’. This is mainly because the UK, unlike America or France, has never had a revolution which led permanently to a totally new system of government. Our most important institutions have developed over hundreds of years. Some people believe that there should be a single document, but others believe an unwritten constitution allows for more flexibility and better government."
           },
           {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "False",
              "id": "T12-12",
              "level": 5.2,
              "question": "MPs can only be contacted at their office in the House of Commons.",
              "options": [
                 "True",
                 "False"
              ],
              "explaination": "You can contact MPs by letter or telephone at their constituency Office, or at their Office in the House of Commons. In addition, many MPs, Assembly members, MSPs and MEPs hold regular local ‘surgeries’, where constituents can go in person to talk about issues that are of concern to them. These surgeries are often advertised in the local newspaper."
           },
           {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "The monarch",
              "id": "T14-10",
              "level": 5.2,
              "question": "Who appoints life peers in the House of Lords?",
              "options": [
                 "The monarch",
                 "The Prime Minister",
                 "The Archbishop of Canterbury",
                 "The Speaker"
              ],
              "explaination": "Since 1958, the Prime Minister has had the power to nominate peers just for their own lifetime. These are called life peers. Life peers are appointed by the monarch on the advice of the Prime Minister. They also include people nominated by the leaders of the other main political parties or by an independent Appointments Commission for non-party peers."
           },
           {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "False",
              "id": "T15-20",
              "level": 5.2,
              "question": "The members of the House of Lords, known as peers, are elected by the people.",
              "options": [
                 "True",
                 "False"
              ],
              "explaination": "Members of the House of Lords, known as peers, are not elected by the people and do not represent a constituency."
           },
           {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "Represent the constituency;Helping to make new law",
              "id": "T17-04",
              "level": 5.2,
              "question": "Which two of below are the responsibility of MP?",
              "options": [
                 "Attend the House of Lord",
                 "Nominate peers in the House of Lord",
                 "Represent the constituency",
                 "Helping to make new law"
              ],
              "explaination": "Voters in each constituency elect their member of Parliament (MP) in a General Election. All of the elected MPs form the House of Commons. MPs have a number of different responsibilities. They:\n-represent everyone in their constituency\n-help to create new laws\n-scrutinise and comment on what the government is doing\n-debate important national issues."
           },
           {
             "star": true,
             "answer": "Constituency",
             "id": "T8-13",
             "level": 5.2,
             "question": "A responsibility of the MPs is to represent everyone in their _______.",
             "options": [
               "County",
               "District",
               "Constituency",
               "Institution"
             ],
             "explaination": "Each MP represents a parliamentary constituency, which is a small area of the country."
           },
           {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "appoint the government after elections",
              "id": "T17-11",
              "level": 5.2,
              "question": "Under constitutional monarchy, the king or the queen has the right to:",
              "options": [
                 "insist on particular policies or actions if Parliament did not agree",
                 "appoint the government after elections",
                 "Rule the country"
              ],
              "explaination": "The UK has a constitutional monarchy. This means that the king or queen does not rule the country but appoints the government, which the people have chosen in a democratic election. The monarch remained very important but was no longer able to insist on particular policies or actions if Parliament did not agree."
           },
           {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "Armed Force",
              "id": "T17-16",
              "level": 5.2,
              "question": "Which is not a Constituency organizations?",
              "options": [
                 "Cabinet",
                 "Parliament",
                 "Police",
                 "Armed Force"
              ],
              "explaination": "Several different parts of government. The main ones are: the monarchy,Parliament (the House of Commons and the House of Lords),the Prime Minister,the cabinet,the judiciary (courts),the police,the civil service,local government."
           },
           {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "The Speaker is neutral and does not represent a political party.",
              "id": "T17-29",
              "level": 5.2,
              "question": "Which of the following statements is correct?",
              "options": [
                 "The Speaker can represent a political party.",
                 "The Speaker is neutral and does not represent a political party."
              ],
              "explaination": "Debates in the House of Commons are chaired by the Speaker. This person is the chief Officer of the House of Commons. The Speaker is neutral and does not represent a political party, even though he or she is an MP, represents a constituency and deals with constituents’ problems like any other MP. The Speaker is chosen by other MPs in a secret ballot."
           },
           {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "is poltiical neutral",
              "id": "T17-43",
              "level": 5.2,
              "question": "The Speaker of the House of Commons _____.",
              "options": [
                 "is not part of the parliament",
                 "is chosen by everyone in the UK in a secret ballot",
                 "is poltiical neutral",
                 "is appointed by Prime Minister"
              ],
              "explaination": "Debates in the House of Commons are chaired by the Speaker."
           },
           {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "Every 5 years",
              "id": "T4-04",
              "level": 5.2,
              "question": "How often are general elections held in the UK?",
              "options": [
                 "Every years",
                 "Every 4 years",
                 "Every 5 years",
                 "Every 10 years"
              ],
              "explaination": "MPs are elected at a General Election, which is held at least every five years."
           },
           {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "The House of Lords;House of Commons",
              "id": "T4-10",
              "level": 5.2,
              "question": "Which two houses form the UK Parliament?",
              "options": [
                 "House of Members",
                 "The House of Lords",
                 "House of Commons",
                 "House of Fraser"
              ],
              "explaination": "The UK Parliament is formed of the House of Commons and the House of Lords."
           },
           {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "By-election",
              "id": "T8-23",
              "level": 5.2,
              "question": "What sort of election takes place when a member of the Parliament (MP) dies or resigns?",
              "options": [
                 "Random selection",
                 "By-election",
                 "Coalition",
                 "‘first past the post’"
              ],
              "explaination": "If an MP dies or resigns, there will be a fresh election, called a byelection, in his or her constituency."
           },
           {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "False",
              "id": "T9-18",
              "level": 5.2,
              "question": "MPs can only be contacted by post.",
              "options": [
                 "True",
                 "False"
              ],
              "explaination": "You can contact MPs by letter or telephone at their constituency Office, or at their Office in the House of Commons. In addition, many MPs, Assembly members, MSPs and MEPs hold regular local ‘surgeries’, where constituents can go in person to talk about issues that are of concern to them. These surgeries are often advertised in the local newspaper."
           }
        ]
    },
    {
        "category": "5.3 The government",
        "questions":
        [
            {
               "star": true,
               "answer": "True",
               "id": "T14-16",
               "level": 5.3,
               "question": "The system of government in the UK is a parliamentary democracy.",
               "options": [
                  "True",
                  "False"
               ],
               "explaination": "The system of government in the UK is a parliamentary democracy. The UK is divided into parliamentary constituencies. Voters in each constituency elect their member of Parliament (MP) in a General Election. All of the elected MPs form the House of Commons."
            },
           {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "60",
              "id": "T10-10",
              "level": 5.3,
              "question": "How many members does the Welsh government have?",
              "options": [
                 "12",
                 "60",
                 "90",
                 "129"
              ],
              "explaination": "The Welsh government and National Assembly for Wales are based in Cardiff, the capital city of Wales. The National Assembly has 60 Assembly members (AMs) and elections are held every four years using a form of proportional representation."
           },
           {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "True",
              "id": "T11-10",
              "level": 5.3,
              "question": "By law, radio and television coverage of the political parties must be balanced and so equal time has to be given to rival viewpoints.",
              "options": [
                 "True",
                 "False"
              ],
              "explaination": ""
           },
           {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "Immigration;Defence",
              "id": "T11-16",
              "level": 5.3,
              "question": "The Northern Ireland Assembly cannot make decisions on which two of the following issues?",
              "options": [
                 "Education",
                 "Immigration",
                 "Defence",
                 "Agriculture"
              ],
              "explaination": "Policy and laws governing defence, foreign affairs, immigration, taxation and social security all remain under central UK government control. However, many other public services, such as education, are controlled by the devolved administrations. The Northern Ireland Assembly can make decisions on issues such as:education,agriculture,the environment,health,social services."
           },
           {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "90",
              "id": "T12-03",
              "level": 5.3,
              "question": "How many members does the Northern Ireland Assembly have?",
              "options": [
                 "33",
                 "60",
                 "90",
                 "129"
              ],
              "explaination": "The Northern Ireland Assembly was established soon after the Belfast Agreement (or Good Friday Agreement) in 1998. There is a power-sharing agreement which distributes ministerial Offices amongst the main parties. The Assembly has 90 elected members, known as MLAs (members of the Legislative Assembly). They are elected with a form of proportional representation."
           },
           {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "False",
              "id": "T12-06",
              "level": 5.3,
              "question": "Towns, cities and rural areas in the UK are governed by government appointed officials.",
              "options": [
                 "True",
                 "False"
              ],
              "explaination": "Towns, cities and rural areas in the UK are governed by democratically elected councils, often called ‘local authorities’. Some areas have both district and county councils, which have different functions. Most large towns and cities have a single local authority."
           },
           {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "They are chosen on merit and are politically neutral",
              "id": "T12-16",
              "level": 5.3,
              "question": "How are civil servants appointed and what political party do they belong to?",
              "options": [
                 "They are chosen randomly and form part of the Conservative party",
                 "They are chosen randomly and are politically neutral",
                 "They are chosen on merit and are politically neutral",
                 "They are chosen on merit and form part of the Liberal Democrats party"
              ],
              "explaination": "Civil servants support the government in developing and implementing its policies. They also deliver public services. Civil servants are accountable to ministers. They are chosen on merit and are politically neutral – they are not political appointees."
           },
           {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "False",
              "id": "T13-14",
              "level": 5.3,
              "question": "In the UK, you have to be 21 years old to be able to vote in a general election.",
              "options": [
                 "True",
                 "False"
              ],
              "explaination": "The present voting age of 18 was set in 1969 and (with a few exceptions) all UK-born and naturalised adult citizens have the right to vote."
           },
           {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "By a system of proportional representation",
              "id": "T14-02",
              "level": 5.3,
              "question": "How are the members of the Northern Ireland Parliament elected?",
              "options": [
                 "Using the first past the post system",
                 "By a system of proportional representation",
                 "Using a system of ranked voting",
                 "Using a runoff system"
              ],
              "explaination": "The Northern Ireland Assembly was established soon after the Belfast Agreement (or Good Friday Agreement) in 1998. The Assembly has 90 elected members, known as MLAs (members of the Legislative Assembly). They are elected with a form of proportional representation."
           },
           {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "Hansard",
              "id": "T14-08",
              "level": 5.3,
              "question": "Proceedings in Parliament are broadcast on television and published in official reports known as:",
              "options": [
                 "Domesday Boo",
                 "Canvassing",
                 "Cabinets",
                 "Hansard"
              ],
              "explaination": "Proceedings in Parliament are broadcast on television and published in official reports called Hansard. Written reports can be found in large libraries and at www.parliament.uk. Most people get information about political issues and events from newspapers (often called ‘the press’), television, radio and the internet."
           },
           {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "No",
              "id": "T14-21",
              "level": 5.3,
              "question": "Are civil servants appointed by the government?",
              "options": [
                 "Yes",
                 "No"
              ],
              "explaination": "Civil servants support the government in developing and implementing its policies. They also deliver public services. Civil servants are accountable to ministers. They are chosen on merit and are politically neutral – they are not political appointees."
           },
           {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "The Home Secretary",
              "id": "T15-22",
              "level": 5.3,
              "question": "Who is responsible for crime, policing and immigration?",
              "options": [
                 "Foreign Secretary",
                 "The Home Secretary",
                 "The Chancellor of the Exchequer",
                 "Secretaries of State"
              ],
              "explaination": "Home Secretary – responsible for crime, policing and immigration\nForeign Secretary – responsible for managing relationships with foreign countries\nChancellor of the Exchequer – responsible for the economy\nother ministers (called ‘Secretaries of State’) responsible for subjects such as education, health and defence."
           },
           {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "False",
              "id": "T17-01",
              "level": 5.3,
              "question": "National Assembly for Wales cannot pass any laws without the agreement of the UK Parliament.",
              "options": [
                 "True",
                 "False"
              ],
              "explaination": "Policy and laws governing defence, foreign affairs, immigration, taxation and social security all remain under central UK government control. However, many other public services, such as education, are controlled by the devolved administrations. The Northern Ireland Assembly can make decisions on issues such as:education,agriculture,the environment,health,social services."
           },
           {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "False",
              "id": "T17-08",
              "level": 5.3,
              "question": "Is the Scottish parliament located in Glasgow?",
              "options": [
                 "True",
                 "False"
              ],
              "explaination": "The Scottish Parliament was formed in 1999. It sits in Edinburgh, the capital city of Scotland."
           },
           {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "Shadow Cabinet",
              "id": "T17-13",
              "level": 5.3,
              "question": "The role of which group of ministers is to challenge the ruling government and offer alternate policies",
              "options": [
                 "Peers",
                 "Opposition",
                 "Shadow Cabinet",
                 "Chancellor of the Exchequer"
              ],
              "explaination": "They form the shadow cabinet and their role is to challenge the government and put forward alternative policies."
           },
           {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "Independents",
              "id": "T17-14",
              "level": 5.3,
              "question": "What are the MPs who do not represent any of the main political parties called?",
              "options": [
                 "Cabinet",
                 "Shadow Cabinet",
                 "Peers",
                 "Independents"
              ],
              "explaination": "There are a few MPs who do not represent any of the main political parties. They are called ‘independents’ and usually represent an issue important to their constituency."
           },
           {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "Education",
              "id": "T17-36",
              "level": 5.3,
              "question": "In what areas of the Northern Ireland Assembly can make decisions?",
              "options": [
                 "Education",
                 "Immigration",
                 "Defence",
                 "Taxation"
              ],
              "explaination": "Policy and laws governing defence, foreign affairs, immigration, taxation and social security all remain under central UK government control. However, many other public services, such as education, are controlled by the devolved administrations. The Northern Ireland Assembly can make decisions on issues such as:education,agriculture,the environment,health,social services."
           },
           {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "Policing",
              "id": "T2-01",
              "level": 5.3,
              "question": "What is the Home Secretary responsible for?",
              "options": [
                 "Education",
                 "Policing",
                 "Defence",
                 "Health"
              ],
              "explaination": "The Home Secretary is responsible for crime, policing and immigration."
           },
           {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "False",
              "id": "T4-21",
              "level": 5.3,
              "question": "You have to be at least 21 years old to stand as MP.",
              "options": [
                 "True",
                 "False"
              ],
              "explaination": "Anyone aged 18 or over can stand for election as an MP but they are unlikely to win unless they have been nominated to represent one of the major political parties."
           },
           {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "10 Downing Street",
              "id": "T4-23",
              "level": 5.3,
              "question": "Where is the official home of the Prime Minister?",
              "options": [
                 "18 Oxford Street",
                 "Houses of Parliament",
                 "Buckingham Palace",
                 "10 Downing Street"
              ],
              "explaination": "The official home of the Prime Minister is 10 Downing Street, in central London, near the Houses of Parliament."
           },
           {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "Television;Radio",
              "id": "T4-24",
              "level": 5.3,
              "question": "By law, which TWO types of media have to give a balanced coverage of all political parties and equal time to rival viewpoints before an election?",
              "options": [
                 "Newspapers",
                 "Television",
                 "Internet",
                 "Radio"
              ],
              "explaination": "By law, radio and television coverage of the political parties must be balanced and so equal time has to be given to rival viewpoints."
           },
           {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "Every week",
              "id": "T6-07",
              "level": 5.3,
              "question": "How often are ‘Prime Minister’s Questions’ held in the parliament?",
              "options": [
                 "Every day",
                 "Every week",
                 "Every two weeks",
                 "Once a month"
              ],
              "explaination": "The leader of the opposition leads his or her party in pointing out what they see as the government’s failures and weaknesses. One important opportunity to do this is at Prime Minister’s Questions, which takes place every week while Parliament is sitting."
           },
           {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "False",
              "id": "T6-12",
              "level": 5.3,
              "question": "Scotland and Wales use a system called ‘individual registration’ where all those entitled to vote must complete their own registration form.",
              "options": [
                 "True",
                 "False"
              ],
              "explaination": "In Northern Ireland a different system operates. This is called ‘individual registration’ and all those entitled to vote must complete their own registration form. Once registered, people stay on the register provided their personal details do not change."
           },
           {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "The Liberal Democrats Party;The Conservative Party",
              "id": "T6-16",
              "level": 5.3,
              "question": "Which two political parties formed a coalition in 2010?",
              "options": [
                 "The Green Party",
                 "The Labour Party",
                 "The Liberal Democrats Party",
                 "The Conservative Party"
              ],
              "explaination": "In May 2010, and for the first time in the UK since February 1974, no political party won an overall majority in the General Election. The Conservative and Liberal Democrat parties formed a coalition and the leader of the Conservative Party, David Cameron, became Prime Minister."
           },
           {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "Health;Education",
              "id": "T7-09",
              "level": 5.3,
              "question": "Which two issues can the devolved administrations pass laws on?",
              "options": [
                 "Health",
                 "Defence",
                 "Social security",
                 "Education"
              ],
              "explaination": "Policy and laws governing defence, foreign affairs, immigration, taxation and social security all remain under central UK government control. However, many other public services, such as education, are controlled by the devolved administrations."
           },
           {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "Crime",
              "id": "T8-04",
              "level": 5.3,
              "question": "Which of the following is a responsibility of the Home Secretary?",
              "options": [
                 "Economy",
                 "Education",
                 "Crime",
                 "Defence"
              ],
              "explaination": "Home Secretary – responsible for crime, policing and immigration"
           },
           {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "Every 4 years",
              "id": "T8-20",
              "level": 5.3,
              "question": "How often are the members of the Welsh government elected?",
              "options": [
                 "Every year",
                 "Every 2 years",
                 "Every 4 years",
                 "Every 5 years"
              ],
              "explaination": "The Welsh government and National Assembly for Wales are based in Cardiff, the capital city of Wales. The National Assembly has 60 Assembly members (AMs) and elections are held every four years using a form of proportional representation."
           },
           {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "True",
              "id": "T9-11",
              "level": 5.3,
              "question": "Northern Ireland uses a system called ‘individual registration’ and all those entitled to vote must complete their own registration form.",
              "options": [
                 "True",
                 "False"
              ],
              "explaination": "In Northern Ireland a different system operates. This is called ‘individual registration’ and all those entitled to vote must complete their own registration form. Once registered, people stay on the register provided their personal details do not change."
           },
           {
             "star": true,
             "answer": "False",
             "id": "T11-13",
             "level": 5.3,
             "question": "The UK government has never suspended the Northern Ireland Assembly.",
             "options": [
               "True",
               "False"
             ],
             "explaination": "The UK government has the power to suspend all devolved assemblies. It has used this power several times in Northern Ireland when local political leaders found it difficult to work together. The Northern Ireland Assembly was elected in 1999 but suspended in 2002."
           },
           {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "Defence;Immigration",
              "id": "T9-12",
              "level": 5.3,
              "question": "Which two of the following policies are not controlled by the devolved administrations?",
              "options": [
                 "Immigration",
                 "Education",
                 "Defence",
                 "Health"
              ],
              "explaination": "Policy and laws governing defence, foreign affairs, immigration, taxation and social security all remain under central UK government control. However, many other public services, such as education, are controlled by the devolved administrations."
           },
           {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "18",
              "id": "T9-13",
              "level": 5.3,
              "question": "How old do citizens of the UK, the Irish Republic or the Commonwealth have to be to stand for public office?",
              "options": [
                 "16",
                 "17",
                 "18",
                 "21"
              ],
              "explaination": "Most citizens of the UK, the Irish Republic or the Commonwealth aged 18 or over can stand for public Office."
           },
           {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "A poll card",
              "id": "T1-17",
              "level": 5.3,
              "question": "What will you be given to vote before a general election takes place?",
              "options": [
                 "A number to queue at the polling station",
                 "A poll card",
                 "A poll tax relief",
                 "An specific time for you to vote"
              ],
              "explaination": "Before the election you will be sent a poll card."
           },
        ]
    },
    {
        "category": "5.4 The UK and international institutions",
        "questions":
        [
           {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "After the Second World War",
              "id": "T16-01",
              "level": 5.4,
              "question": "When was the United Nations set up?",
              "options": [
                 "Before the First World War",
                 "After the First World War",
                 "Before the Second World War",
                 "After the Second World War"
              ],
              "explaination": "The UK is part of the United Nations (UN), an international organisation with more than 190 countries as members. The UN was set up after the Second World War and aims to prevent war and promote international peace and security."
           },
           {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "An association of countries that support each other and work together towards shared goals in democracy and development.",
              "id": "T16-21",
              "level": 5.4,
              "question": "What is the Commonwealth?",
              "options": [
                 "An association of countries that responsible for the protection and promotion of human rights in those countries.",
                 "An association of countries that support each other and work together towards shared goals in democracy and development.",
                 "A group of European and North American countries that have agreed to help each other if they come under attack.",
                 "An international organization that aims to prevent war and promote international peace and security."
              ],
              "explaination": "The Commonwealth is an association of countries that support each other and work together towards shared goals in democracy and development. Most member states were once part of the British Empire, although a few countries which were not have also joined."
           },
           {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "maintain peace between all of its members",
              "id": "T17-28",
              "level": 5.4,
              "question": "NATO is designed to ensure what?",
              "options": [
                 "protection and promotion of human rights",
                 "shared goals in democracy and development",
                 "prevent war and promote international peace and security",
                 "maintain peace between all of its members"
              ],
              "explaination": "The UK is also a member of NATO. NATO is a group of European and North American countries that have agreed to help each other if they come under attack. It also aims to maintain peace between all of its members."
           }
        ]
    },
    {
        "category": "5.5 Respecting the law",
        "questions": [
            {
               "star": true,
               "answer": "Go to the Police station directly;Write to the Chief Constable of the police force involved",
               "id": "T11-17",
               "level": 5.5,
               "question": "What should you do to make a complaint about the police (choose two answers)?",
               "options": [
                  "Go to the Police station directly",
                  "Write to your MP",
                  "Write a complaint letter to the House of Commons",
                  "Write to the Chief Constable of the police force involved"
               ],
               "explaination": "Anyone can make a complaint about the police by going to a police station or writing to the Chief Constable of the police force involved. Complaints can also be made to an independent body."
            },
            {
               "star": true,
               "answer": "Your local police force",
               "id": "T3-07",
               "level": 5.5,
               "question": "If you think someone is trying to persuade you to join an extremist or terrorist activity, who should you contact?",
               "options": [
                  "Your family",
                  "Your local MP",
                  "Your local police force",
                  "The Home Office"
               ],
               "explaination": "If you think someone is trying to persuade you to join an extremist or terrorist cause, you should notify your local police force."
            },
            {
               "star": true,
               "answer": "Criminal offences",
               "id": "T4-19",
               "level": 5.5,
               "question": "Racial crime and smoking in public places are examples of:",
               "options": [
                  "Civil offences",
                  "Criminal offences"
               ],
               "explaination": "Examples of criminal laws are: carrying a weapon, selling or buying drugs, racial crime, selling tobacco to anyone under the age of 18, smoking in public places, sell alcohol to anyone who is under 18 or to buy alcohol for people who are under the age of 18, drinking in alcohol-free zones."
            },
            {
               "star": true,
               "answer": "False",
               "id": "T5-12",
               "level": 5.5,
               "question": "Complaints against the police can only be made by writing to the Police Complaints Commissioner.",
               "options": [
                  "True",
                  "False"
               ],
               "explaination": "Anyone can make a complaint about the police by going to a police station or writing to the Chief Constable of the police force involved. Complaints can also be made to an independent body."
            },
            {
               "star": true,
               "answer": "Discrimination in the workplace",
               "id": "T5-16",
               "level": 5.5,
               "question": "Which of the following is an example of civil law?",
               "options": [
                  "Discrimination in the workplace",
                  "To sell tobacco products to anyone under the age of 18",
                  "To buy alcohol for people who are under the age of 18",
                  "To carry a weapon of any kind, even if it is for self-defence"
               ],
               "explaination": "Examples of civil laws are:\nHousing law: this includes disputes between landlords and tenants over issues such as repairs and eviction.\nConsumer rights: an example of this is a dispute about faulty goods or services.\nEmployment law: these cases include disputes over wages and cases of unfair dismissal or discrimination in the workplace.\nDebt: people might be taken to court if they owe money to someone."
            },
            {
               "star": true,
               "answer": "Smoking in public places where it is not allowed",
               "id": "T7-07",
               "level": 5.5,
               "question": "Which of the following is an example of criminal offence?",
               "options": [
                  "Disputes about an unfair dismissal in the workplace",
                  "A dispute between the landlord and the tenants who have not paid the rent",
                  "Disputes about faulty goods or services",
                  "Smoking in public places where it is not allowed"
               ],
               "explaination": "Examples of criminal laws are: carrying a weapon, selling or buying drugs, racial crime, selling tobacco to anyone under the age of 18, smoking in public places, sell alcohol to anyone who is under 18 or to buy alcohol for people who are under the age of 18, drinking in alcohol-free zones."
            },
            {
               "star": true,
               "answer": "False",
               "id": "T8-03",
               "level": 5.5,
               "question": "Police complaints can only be made by writing to the Chief Constable of the police force involved.",
               "options": [
                  "True",
                  "False"
               ],
               "explaination": "Anyone can make a complaint about the police by going to a police station or writing to the Chief Constable of the police force involved. Complaints can also be made to an independent body."
            }
         ]
    },
    {
        "category": "5.6 The Role of the Courts",
        "questions": [
            {
               "star": true,
               "answer": "Solicitors' charges are usually based on how much time they spend on a case",
               "id": "T1-18",
               "level": 5.6,
               "question": "Which of the following statements is correct?",
               "options": [
                  "Solicitors' charges are usually based on the nature of a case and its importance",
                  "Solicitors' charges are usually based on how much time they spend on a case"
               ],
               "explaination": "Solicitors’ charges are usually based on how much time they spend of a case."
            },
            {
               "star": true,
               "answer": "False",
               "id": "T10-11",
               "level": 5.6,
               "question": "The names or photographs of young people found guilty of a crime can be published in newspapers or used by the media.",
               "options": [
                  "True",
                  "False"
               ],
               "explaination": "The most serious cases will go to the Crown Court. The parents or carers of the young person are expected to attend the hearing. Members of the public are not allowed in Youth Courts, and the name or photographs of the accused young person cannot be published in newspapers or used by the media."
            },
            {
               "star": true,
               "answer": "District judges;Specially trained magistrates",
               "id": "T16-06",
               "level": 5.6,
               "question": "Who can hear cases in Youth Courts in England, Wales and Northern Ireland (two answers)?",
               "options": [
                  "Social workers",
                  "Members of the public",
                  "District judges",
                  "Specially trained magistrates"
               ],
               "explaination": "In England, Wales and Northern Ireland, if an accused person is aged 10 to 17, the case is normally heard in a Youth Court in front of up to three specially trained magistrates or a District Judge. The most serious cases will go to the Crown Court. The parents or carers of the young person are expected to attend the hearing. Members of the public are not allowed in Youth Courts."
            },
            {
               "star": true,
               "answer": "£3,000",
               "id": "T16-14",
               "level": 5.6,
               "question": "What is the maximum amount you can claim through the small claims procedure in Scotland and Northern Ireland?",
               "options": [
                  "£1,000",
                  "£3,000",
                  "£5,000",
                  "£10,000"
               ],
               "explaination": "The small claims procedure is an informal way of helping people to settle minor disputes without spending a lot of time and money using a lawyer. This procedure is used for claims of less than £5,000 in England and Wales and £3,000 in Scotland and Northern Ireland."
            },
            {
               "star": true,
               "answer": "True",
               "id": "T17-32",
               "level": 5.6,
               "question": "The judge of magistrate court in Northern Ireland is legally qualified.",
               "options": [
                  "True",
                  "False"
               ],
               "explaination": "In Northern Ireland, cases are heard by a District Judge or Deputy District Judge, who is legally qualified and paid. In England, Wales and Scotland they usually work unpaid and do not need legal qualifications."
            },
            {
               "star": true,
               "answer": "12",
               "id": "T2-15",
               "level": 5.6,
               "question": "How many members does a jury have in England, Wales and Northern Ireland?",
               "options": [
                  "10",
                  "12",
                  "15",
                  "25"
               ],
               "explaination": "In England, Wales and Northern Ireland a jury has 12 members, and in Scotland a jury has 15 members."
            },
            {
               "star": true,
               "answer": "Magistrates’ Court",
               "id": "T2-23",
               "level": 5.6,
               "question": "Which court deals with minor criminal cases in England, Wales and Northern Ireland?",
               "options": [
                  "High Court",
                  "Crown Court",
                  "Magistrates’ Court",
                  "Justice of the Peace Court"
               ],
               "explaination": "In England, Wales and Northern Ireland, most minor criminal cases are dealt with in a Magistrates’ Court. In Scotland, minor criminal offences go to a Justice of the Peace Court."
            },
            {
               "star": true,
               "answer": "The Justice of the Peace Court",
               "id": "T6-20",
               "level": 5.6,
               "question": "Which court deals with minor criminal offences in Scotland?",
               "options": [
                  "The Crown Court",
                  "The Sheriff Court",
                  "The Magistrates' Court",
                  "The Justice of the Peace Court"
               ],
               "explaination": "In England, Wales and Northern Ireland, most minor criminal cases are dealt with in a Magistrates’ Court. In Scotland, minor criminal offences go to a Justice of the Peace Court."
            },
            {
               "star": true,
               "answer": "15",
               "id": "T7-22",
               "level": 5.6,
               "question": "How many members form a jury in Scotland?",
               "options": [
                  "10",
                  "12",
                  "15",
                  "20"
               ],
               "explaination": "A jury is made up of members of the public chosen at random from the local electoral register. In England, Wales and Northern Ireland a jury has 12 members, and in Scotland a jury has 15 members."
            },
            {
               "star": true,
               "answer": "An informal way of helping people to settle minor disputes without spending a lot of time and money using a lawyer",
               "id": "T9-22",
               "level": 5.6,
               "question": "What is the small claims procedure?",
               "options": [
                  "An informal way of helping people to settle minor disputes without spending a lot of time and money using a lawyer",
                  "A procedure that helps people to make small home insurance claims in certain circumstances"
               ],
               "explaination": "The small claims procedure is an informal way of helping people to settle minor disputes without spending a lot of time and money using a lawyer."
            }
         ]
    },
    {
        "category": "5.7 Fundamental Principles",
        "questions": [
            {
               "star": true,
               "answer": "Yes",
               "id": "T15-07",
               "level": 5.7,
               "question": "Can court orders be obtained to protect a person from being forced into a marriage?",
               "options": [
                  "Yes",
                  "No"
               ],
               "explaination": "Forced Marriage Protection Orders were introduced in 2008 for England, Wales and Northern Ireland under the Forced Marriage (Civil Protection) Act 2007. Court orders can be obtained to protect a person from being forced into a marriage, or to protect a person in a forced marriage. Similar Protection Orders were introduced in Scotland in November 2011."
            },
            {
               "star": true,
               "answer": "True",
               "id": "T15-24",
               "level": 5.7,
               "question": "Anyone who is violent towards their partner – whether they are a man or a woman, married or living together – can be prosecuted.",
               "options": [
                  "True",
                  "False"
               ],
               "explaination": "Anyone who is violent towards their partner – whether they are a man or woman, married or living together – can be prosecuted. Any man who forces a woman to have sex, including a woman’s husband, can be charged with rape."
            },
            {
               "star": true,
               "answer": "True",
               "id": "T5-20",
               "level": 5.7,
               "question": "If a husband forces his wife to have sex he can be charged with rape.",
               "options": [
                  "True",
                  "False"
               ],
               "explaination": "Any man who forces a woman to have sex, including a woman’s husband, can be charged with rape."
            },
            {
               "star": true,
               "answer": "True",
               "id": "T8-15",
               "level": 5.7,
               "question": "Female genital mutilation (FGM) or taking a girl or woman abroad for FGM is illegal in the UK and it is a criminal offence.",
               "options": [
                  "True",
                  "False"
               ],
               "explaination": "Female genital mutilation (FGM), also known as cutting or female circumcision, is illegal in the UK. Practising FGM or taking a girl or woman abroad for FGM is a criminal offence."
            }
         ]
    },
    {
        "category": "5.8 Taxation",
        "questions":
        [
           {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "Documents that prove that you have permission to work in the UK;Documents that prove your identity",
              "id": "T6-24",
              "level": 5.8,
              "question": "Which two documents do you need to apply for a National Insurance number?",
              "options": [
                 "Documents that prove your identity",
                 "Documents that prove that you have permission to work in the UK",
                 "A document with your address on it, such as a tenancy agreement",
                 "A contract from your employer"
              ],
              "explaination": "You will usually need documents that prove your identity and that you have permission to work in the UK."
           },
           {
              "star": true,
              "answer": "Contact the Department for Work and Pensions (DWP)",
              "id": "T7-20",
              "level": 5.8,
              "question": "What do you need to do to apply for a National Insurance Number?",
              "options": [
                 "Contact your local MP",
                 "Contact the NHS",
                 "Contact the Department for Work and Pensions (DWP)",
                 "Ask you employer to get it for you"
              ],
              "explaination": "If you have permission to work in the UK, you will need to telephone the Department for Work and Pensions (DWP) to arrange to get a National Insurance number."
           }
        ]
    },
    {
        "category": "5.9 Driving",
        "questions": [
            {
               "star": true,
               "answer": "A valid driving licence",
               "id": "T10-08",
               "level": 5.9,
               "question": "What do you need to drive in the UK?",
               "options": [
                  "An ‘L’ plate",
                  "An ‘R’ plate",
                  "A National Insurance Number",
                  "A valid driving licence"
               ],
               "explaination": "In the UK, you must be at least 17 years old to drive a car or motor cycle and you must have a driving licence to drive on public roads."
            },
            {
               "star": true,
               "answer": "17",
               "id": "T15-19",
               "level": 5.9,
               "question": "What is the minimum age required to drive a motor cycle?",
               "options": [
                  "16",
                  "17",
                  "18",
                  "21"
               ],
               "explaination": "In the UK, you must be at least 17 years old to drive a car or motor cycle and you must have a driving licence to drive on public roads."
            },
            {
               "star": true,
               "answer": "16 years old",
               "id": "T16-12",
               "level": 5.9,
               "question": "How old do you have to be to drive a moped in the UK?",
               "options": [
                  "16 years old",
                  "17 years old",
                  "18 years old",
                  "21 years old"
               ],
               "explaination": "You need to be at least 16 years old to ride a moped."
            },
            {
               "star": true,
               "answer": "17",
               "id": "T17-45",
               "level": 5.9,
               "question": "What is the minimum age required to drive a vehicle?",
               "options": [
                  "16",
                  "17",
                  "18",
                  "21"
               ],
               "explaination": "In the UK, you must be at least 17 years old to drive a car or motor cycle and you must have a driving licence to drive on public roads."
            }
         ]
    },
    {
        "category": "5.11 How you can support your Community",
        "questions": [
            {
               "star": true,
               "answer": "18",
               "id": "T1-14",
               "level": 5.11,
               "question": "What is the minimum age required to serve on a jury?",
               "options": [
                  "16",
                  "17",
                  "18",
                  "21"
               ],
               "explaination": "Anyone who is on the electoral register and is aged 18 to 70 can be asked to serve on a jury."
            },
            {
               "star": true,
               "answer": "Randomly from the electoral register",
               "id": "T1-15",
               "level": 5.11,
               "question": "How is a jury selected?",
               "options": [
                  "From the NHS registration system",
                  "Randomly from the telephone directory",
                  "From a postcode selection",
                  "Randomly from the electoral register"
               ],
               "explaination": "As well as getting the right to vote, people on the electoral register are randomly selected to serve on a jury. Anyone who is on the electoral register and is aged 18 to 70 can be asked to do this."
            },
            {
               "star": true,
               "answer": "Friends of the Earth",
               "id": "T11-06",
               "level": 5.11,
               "question": "Which of the following charities helps the environment?",
               "options": [
                  "Friends of the Earth",
                  "Crisis and Shelter",
                  "NSPCC",
                  "PDSA"
               ],
               "explaination": "There are thousands of active charities and voluntary organisations in the UK. They include charities working with older people (such as Age UK), with children (for example, the National Society for the Prevention of Cruelty to Children (NSPCC)), and with the homeless (for example, Crisis and Shelter). There are also medical research charities (for example, Cancer Research UK), environmental charities (including the National Trust and Friends of the Earth) and charities working with animals (such as the People’s Dispensary for Sick Animals (PDSA))."
            },
            {
               "star": true,
               "answer": "False",
               "id": "T12-18",
               "level": 5.11,
               "question": "You have to be at least 21 years old to serve on a jury.",
               "options": [
                  "True",
                  "False"
               ],
               "explaination": "People on the electoral register are randomly selected to serve on a jury. Anyone who is on the electoral register and is aged 18 to 70 can be asked to do this."
            },
            {
               "star": true,
               "answer": "16- and 17-year-olds",
               "id": "T16-08",
               "level": 5.11,
               "question": "Who can apply for the National Citizen Service programme?",
               "options": [
                  "All ages",
                  "15- and 16-year-olds",
                  "16- and 17-year-olds",
                  "17- and 18-year-olds"
               ],
               "explaination": "There are many opportunities for young people to volunteer and receive accreditation which will help them to develop their skills. These include the National Citizen Service programme, which gives 16- and 17-year-olds the opportunity to enjoy outdoor activities, develop their skills and take part in a community project."
            },
            {
               "star": true,
               "answer": "False",
               "id": "T3-08",
               "level": 5.11,
               "question": "It is compulsory for 16 and 17-year-olds to join the National Citizen Service programme.",
               "options": [
                  "True",
                  "False"
               ],
               "explaination": "There are many opportunities for young people to volunteer and receive accreditation which will help them to develop their skills. These include the National Citizen Service programme, which gives 16- and 17-year-olds the opportunity to enjoy outdoor activities, develop their skills and take part in a community project."
            },
            {
               "star": true,
               "answer": "setting the strategic direction of the school;monitoring and evaluating school performance",
               "id": "T3-17",
               "level": 5.11,
               "question": "Which two of the following are key roles of school governors?",
               "options": [
                  "monitoring and evaluating school performance",
                  "giving awards to the best students of the school",
                  "setting the strategic direction of the school",
                  "monitoring student's behaviour"
               ],
               "explaination": "Governors and school boards have an important part to play in raising school standards. They have three key roles:\nsetting the strategic direction of the school\nensuring accountability\nmonitoring and evaluating school performance"
            },
            {
               "star": true,
               "answer": "The electoral register",
               "id": "T5-06",
               "level": 5.11,
               "question": "Where should you register if you want to become part of a jury?",
               "options": [
                  "The British Embassy",
                  "The electoral register",
                  "Your local church",
                  "The NHS"
               ],
               "explaination": "People on the electoral register are randomly selected to serve on a jury. Therefore, if you want to be selected to form part of a jury you have to be on the electoral register and be between 18 to 70 years old."
            },
            {
               "star": true,
               "answer": "An environmental charity",
               "id": "T5-19",
               "level": 5.11,
               "question": "What sort of charity is ‘Friends of the Earth’?",
               "options": [
                  "A charity working with pets",
                  "A charity working with older people",
                  "A medical research charity",
                  "An environmental charity"
               ],
               "explaination": "environmental charities (including the National Trust and Friends of the Earth)"
            },
            {
               "star": true,
               "answer": "Persuading people to vote for a political party",
               "id": "T5-22",
               "level": 5.11,
               "question": "Which of the following actions is known as “canvassing”?",
               "options": [
                  "Persuading people to vote for a political party",
                  "Donating blood to help people",
                  "Caring for animals at a local rescue shelter",
                  "Volunteering for an environmental charity"
               ],
               "explaination": "for instance, by handing out leaflets in the street or by knocking on people’s doors and asking for their support. This is called ‘canvassing’."
            },
            {
               "star": true,
               "answer": "ensuring accountability;setting the strategic direction of the school",
               "id": "T17-46",
               "level": 5.11,
               "question": "What are the functions of school governors? (Choose two answers)",
               "options": [
                  "ensuring accountability",
                  "giving awards to the best students",
                  "setting the strategic direction of the school",
                  "monitoring student's behaviour"
               ],
               "explaination": "Governors and school boards have an important part to play in raising school standards. They have three key roles:\nsetting the strategic direction of the school\nensuring accountability\nmonitoring and evaluating school performance"
            },
         ]
    }
]

